<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere to the last tempest and villanie of the League, vpon the slanders which were imprinted by the same, against the French king Intituled: A declaration of the crimes whereinto the Catholikes do fall, in taking the king of Nauarre his part. Translated out of French into English by T.H.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1593</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843972</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843972</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8747</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20188)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8747)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 166:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere to the last tempest and villanie of the League, vpon the slanders which were imprinted by the same, against the French king Intituled: A declaration of the crimes whereinto the Catholikes do fall, in taking the king of Nauarre his part. Translated out of French into English by T.H.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Scarlet] for Cuthbert Burby, and are to bee solde at his shop vnder Saint Mildreds Church in the Poultrie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of M4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sainte Ligue (1576-1593) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8747:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8747:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE TO THE LAST TEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PEST AND VILLANIE OF THE League, vpon the ſlanders which were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed by the ſame, againſt the French king.</p>
            <p>INTITVLED: <hi>A Declaration of the crimes whereinto the Catholikes do fall, in taking the king of Nauarre his part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French into Engliſh by T.H.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>SIC CREDE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for Cuthbert Burby, and are to bee ſolde at his ſhop vnder Saint Mildreds Church in the Poultrie. 1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:8747:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8747:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y diuine and humane right, <hi>HENRIE of Bourbon,</hi> ought to be acknowledged of all kings, princes, Lordes, and common-wealths of Chriſtendome, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the naturall French-men, the moſt chriſtian king of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and Nauarre.</p>
            <p n="2">2 And ſo, as he ought to be aſsiſted by them in his defence againſt the Spaniard, chiefe of the League, who is riſen vp to ſuppreſſe the libertie, as well of the Church, as of the French gouernment.</p>
            <p n="3">3 All thoſe which do diſcharge themſelues of ſuch a dutie, do obey the commaundement giuen by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Ieſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="4">4 All thoſe which doo the contrarie, are declared to be ſeditious, mutinous, and rebellious, by the expreſſe word of God, and by the holy Articles of the holy Catholique and Chriſtian church.</p>
            <p n="5">5 They alſo declare themſelues enimies of nature, and violaters of the fundamentall lawes of the realme.</p>
            <p n="6">6 By their looſenes, rebellion, &amp; treaſon, they tread
<pb facs="tcp:8747:3"/>downe his honour, dignitie and the excellencie of his name.</p>
            <p n="7">7 They manifeſt themſelues fauters of heretikes, murderers of their king, &amp; vſurpers and deſtroiers of his Crowne.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Conſequently, they are ſciſmatiques, diuiding in peeces the three eſtates of the realme, the which they doo perpetually deſolate, and ſend the poore ſoules into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="9">9 They are execrable periurers, breaking the oath which they owe to God, to their king, to their Countrie.</p>
            <p n="10">10 They cauſe this realme to be ſtinking and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, to all the nations of the world, by their vnnaturall and diſhoneſt rebellion.</p>
            <p n="11">11 All naturall French-men, which doo ſtudie to giue themſelues to the obſeruation of the three firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, declare themſelues faithfull and affectionated to the glorie of God, to the defence of his religion, and to the conſeruation and good of their Countrie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8747:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSWERE TO THE laſt tempeſt and villanie of the League, vpon the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which were imprinted by the ſame, againſt the French King, intituled: A Declaration of the crimes, whereinto the Catholiques doo fall, in taking the king of Nauarre his part.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the yeere of our Lorde God, 1585. ſaith the League,
<note place="margin">Apo 13</note> came forth of the depth a hideous monſter, which hauing vndertaken to combat with &amp; beate down the ſtate of France, tooke for material ſword, the mines of gold and ſiluer, hidden within the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and dens of the new world. Afterwardes the yron and ſteele of the Pirenee and Alpe mountaines, together with the moſt faire, exquiſite, and moſt excellent worke, that the ſuperficies of the earth could produce out of the regions of Spaine, Portugall, Piemont, Italy, Scicilia, and Sardaigne, with a great number of other Iſles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces. By this, the general conducter of the leagued band pretended and deliberated to vſurpe, not onely the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of France, England, and Scotland, but all other of Chriſtendome. From the which practiſed tyrannie, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe proceeded, but a ridiculous dwarfe, like to the teeming of the mountaines in olde time. And ſithence it is come to paſſe, that the deſperate children of Moab, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their naturall weapon to be ſhort, thought good to take the ſpirituall of Balaam, thereby to tourne awaie the French-men from the obedience which they owe to their prince:
<note place="margin">Num. 22.</note> euen as the falſe prophet woulde haue cauſed the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8747:4"/>people of Iſrael to turne from their obedience, which they did owe to God. Alſo heere ought not to bee omitted the ſuperlatiue craft and ſubtilty, which they haue vſed, going about to drawe the Germanes to take their part, namely, thoſe of the confeſſion of Ausbourge, the which they hold for heretikes. To whome Pope Sixtus cauſed to be tolde, that if they would acknowledge the dignitie of his ſeate, that in other things he would declare them tollerable. Yea euen vnto a Councell. By this meanes the League, beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging as well with the good as with the wicked, haue prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the ſaying of the Poet, <hi>Flectere ſi nequo ſuperos, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeronta mouebo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg.</note> If I cannot bend the Gods of heauen to helpe me, I will prouoke the deuils of hell. The demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of which iniquities, are therefore moſt neceſſary, ſeeing that theſe leaguers wold do in like ſort to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men of France, which accompanie the king, as the dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of India doe to the Elephants, when as by dazeling them, they cauſe them to fall. Fearing then that ſome ſuch accident ſhould happen to anie the well affectionate to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the king,
<note place="margin">Plin. li. 8. ca. 12.</note> wee ſhoulde cauſe in like ſorte, that theſe dragons may ſall themſelues, beeing quaſhed aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnder the Elephants, when as by theſe refutations and anſweres, which wee produce againſt the Articles of this traiterous, ſeditious, and leagued Monke, ſhall bee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the iuſt vocation of thoſe which are armed, as well for the defence of their king, as of their Countrie. The which Articles are thirteene in number. And as for the firſt he ſayth, that the Catholikes helping the king, (theſe are his tearmes) doe againſt the commaundement and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word of God: in confirmation whereof, hee allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ſeuen textes out of the holy Scripture, afterwardes holding it for a thing knowen and confeſſed, that the king is an heretike, he pretendeth to maintaine his conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that is, that he is vncapable and vnworthie to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the crowne of France.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8747:4"/>
            <p>Now let vs ſee whether this be to the matter, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he turneth awaie from the ſame texts, as a prophane man, or not, And firſt to proue in generall the falſehoode of theſe Articles, which concerne all the crime of hereſie, from the which this ſlanderer of dignities doth accuſe his king. We ſaie, that the vice called by the Dialecticians, <hi>Petitio principij,</hi> doth declare a manifeſt ignorance,
<note place="margin">Iud. ver. 8.</note> in the arte of diſputing, that is, when one would argue and affirme without proofe or reaſon. And paſſing further, we adde, that there commeth a deuilliſh rage between, when the truth is called a lie. Within the which two vices, this Leaguer and pretended great diſputer, doth throw down himſelfe headlong from all ſpeech. If hee obiecteth that the king hath beene iudged and declared an heretike, by the Eccleſiaſticall Romanes, little children will anſwere him, that the contrarie partie cannot bee iudge: alſo, that the accuſed ought to be heard, before he bee condemned. If he replieth, that all this hath beene done, let him ſaie when? But hee knoweth not. Euen as the houſe of Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, and the Romane Conſiſtorie ſhal teſtifie, which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing enterpriſed to put the Crowne vppon the Guiſe his head, had neede of the falſe pretence of hereſie, thereby to take it from the king. But let vs come to the point. All the worlde knoweth, that the king is accuſed of hereſie by this Monke, and his like: foraſmuch as hee ſayth and holdeth for certaine, that the Romiſh church hath need of reformation: vpon the which propoſition is demaunded, wherefore the king raigning, ſhall bee ſooner accuſed of hereſie, than infinite others of his like, &amp; others as wel in Europe, Aſia, or Affrica. Beſides that which hath beene ſayde elſe where, wee faie, that in our region, the laſt King conſtrayned (but too late) to knowe this truth, had giuen charge to a learned perſonage, to ſet foorth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Articles, concerning the neceſſitie of reforming the Church.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:8747:5"/>
            <p>The laſt Duke of Sauoy, ſayd to an Italian, named Caſtro Caro, profeſſing the reformed religion, Thou doeſt wel to maintaine thy faith. Afterwards he placed him as gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ouer the vallyes of Angrongne.
<note place="margin">Apol for Herod.</note> A Duke of Florence, with like purpoſe anſwered the Ambaſſadour of the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan of Egypt, that in Chriſtendome the fooles were ſhut vp in Monaſteries. The Venetians haue of long time dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the perſecutions of the Popes. The beſt part of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian kings doe confirme this truth, and the noble men, in deede as much, for it is proued, that there are a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gentlemen throughout Europe, which do euen grone and breath after this reformation. If we come to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons, the quantitie of them ſwarming out of the Couents and monaſteries, doeth likewiſe preach on high the ſame thing vnto vs. The like alſo is found by the Popes being conſtrained to produce ſuch a like kinde of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, when as one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpon the abuſe of the Romane Church, which was obiected and proued to him, ſayde to the proteſtant Princes of Germanie, that his intention was to vnderſtand it,
<note place="margin">Sleidan.</note> and remedie it. To whom it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that that did not appertaine to one Biſhop alone. As for philoſophers, councellers of lawe-rights, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the third eſtate, knowing the ſame truth, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, will be found euerie where ſuch a great number, that they will be innumerable. In Aſia, an infinite number of Iewes doe deferre their conuerſion to the Chriſtian reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for the great abuſes and idolatries which they ſee in the Romiſh church. Let vs paſſe into Affrica, then Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Iohn, great gouernour ouer the Ethiopians, making profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, verifieth the ſame by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall permiſſion of holy matrimonie, inſtituted by God, &amp; by the intire diſtribution which the Biſhops doe make of the ſacred ſignes of the holy ſupper, following the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Ieſus Chriſt. What will then this malecontent ſaie, when as for this cauſe onely hee accuſeth his king of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8747:5"/>hereſie, ſeeing that ſo many Monarchies, Princes, Lordes, Prelates of the Church, Councellors, Philoſophers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great, godly, and learned perſonages, throughout all Europe, haue holden, ſayd, reproued, &amp; confeſſed the ſame truth: the which hath beene confirmed by ſo many Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and ſo many arguments, that it is impoſſible for the gainſaiers to anſwere them. The which doctors and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, durſt and dare maintaine and proue, that if there be anie Prince in the world, clere and purged from the crime of hereſie, it is our king: for following the greateſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Chriſtian religion, as euer hath beene ſithence the death of the Apoſtles. That it is ſo, thou ſhalt finde by reading and conſidering the profeſſion of faith, which he hath ſhewed towards the two laſt kings, which is come to light a long time ſithence. Therefore take a little paines with patience, to conferre it with the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <p>Now let vs come to the examination of the firſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, conteining, as we haue ſayde, ſeuen texts of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with the which this ligall Monke woulde helpe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for his better reiecting the king, if he could. The firſt therefore is taken out of the ſeuententh Chapter of Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronomie,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17.17</note> where it is commanded to the people of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael, to conſtitute ouer them the king whome the Lorde their God ſhould chuſe, compriſed in the couenant which he had contracted with him: from the which place, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aforeſayd Monke doth drawe his concluſion, as aforeſaid, that is to ſaie, that the king for being an heretike, ought not to be admitted to the crowne of France, no more then in oldettme a Pagan might to that of the Iewes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſaith he) the lawe of Moſes, concerning the election of the kings of Iſrael, is morall, and by conſequence, doth binde all Chriſtians to the obſeruation of the ſame. The anſwere to this is, that ſeeing Phiſicke muſt be applied to the bodie that is diſeaſed, let vs put the caſe, whether the queſtion was, concerning a king being an Infidell, or an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8747:6"/>heretike. For the regard, namely, of ſuch a ſoueraigne, I denie the propoſition, the which I maintain to be falſe, for foure reſons to be conſidered in the examination and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the text,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17</note> where Moſes ſaith thus, Thou ſhalt make him king ouer thee, whome the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe, from amongſt thy brethren: thou ſhalt not ſet a ſtranger ouer thee, which is not thy brother. Where, firſt of all is to bee vnderſtoode, that the king which the Lorde woulde giue vnto his people, called in the Scripture, the annointed of the Lord, ſhould be choſen after another fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and to another end than others were. Therefore Moſes ſayd, that God himſelfe woulde chooſe this king, differing from them of other nations, for that hee woulde haue him repreſent and figure the Meſſias, his ſonne, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing king euerlaſting, and redeemer of the world, and that he would haue him to raigne ouer an holy nation: which priuiledge giueth vs to vnderſtand, that theſe ſacred kings were holy, and ſeparated from others. Wherefore Moſes in this text,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 10</note> and the hiſtorie of the Kings doe witneſſe, that theyr election proceeded from God, &amp; not from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for which reſpects there was a ſeparation and a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence put betweene them and others: So as is ſeene in the election of Saul,
<note place="margin">1. Chron 28. Iug. 9</note> Dauid, and Salomon. The cauſe why A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech being before appointed king of Sichem, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but a while, was for that, that hee was not ſo called of God: the time of the kings being not yet come. Where it appeareth, that ſuch proceedinges are not conuenient at this daie, for other nations. If thou doeſt replie, that chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian kings haue one and the ſelfe ſame holines, as thoſe of the Iewes had, proceeding from one common God, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that it ſufficeth, to proue that the Chriſtian nations neuer had this particular commandement, nor this ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promiſe, to haue power alwayes to conſtitute ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a king of their owne religion, ſo giuen of GOD, this is a priuiledge onely which the Iewes had: for the Chriſtians
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8747:6"/>haue ben, and are bound by the generall commandement of God, to abide ſubiect to their Princes, which hee hath giuen them, of what religion ſoeuer they haue ben or be, as ſhall be more at large diſcuſſed in his place. To that which remaineth, thou oughteſt to proue, that this realme is a choſen kingdome, and that the Eccleſiaſticall Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, ioyned with ſome number of ignorant people, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by them, haue this right of election, whereof thou ſpeakeſt: ſuch proues are not in the ſtrength of all your Sorbonne. Beholde then the firſt reaſon, ſufficing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the falſehood of thy Commentarie. And ſo I come forward to the ſecond, drawen from the nature of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ouer whome the aforeſayd king ought to bee appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where Moſes ſaith thus, Thou ſhalt not ſet ouer them, &amp;c. Inferring by this Pronoune, that amongſt theſe priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and ſpeciall graces, which God woulde giue vnto his people, he would giue them a king, hauing the quality of a brother, and making profeſſion of the ſame religion which they did, for the better diſtinguiſhing and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them from other nations, the which ſhould carrie the ſame common markes of alliance and adoption,
<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note> and alſo for want whereof, it was ſayd in Geneſis, that euerie man childe, not circumciſed, ſhould be cut off. This was not then, neither hath beene ſithence common to anie other nation, for all men knowe, that God by the preaching of his Goſpell, hath neuer called at once whole nations to the knowledge of him: and that for the moſt part, he hath rather and firſt of all conuerted the ſubiects, yea, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſort from amongſt the ſayd ſubiects, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth to the Corinthians, where it appeareth,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> that the faithfull had neither right nor power to appoint a king o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer themſelues, of theyr religion. It behoueth vs then, to holde this reſolution for a maxime in diuinitie, that God onely calleth whome he pleaſeth, to the knowledge of his truth, and giueth the kingdomes of the earth to whom it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8747:7"/>ſeemeth him good, ſometimes to a beleeuing Prince, and ſometimes to an Infidel. The ſoueraigne God, ſayth Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, hath power ouer the kingdomes, and there placeth whome he will, therefore after Nabuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> donoſor hee pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Balſaſar, Darius, &amp; Cyrus, all Pagans. As alſo ſithence the death of Ieſus Chriſt, of long continuance he hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther called Pagan Princes to gouerne the Empire, than Chriſtians, the which ſucceeded one another by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and pleaſure of him, euen as Saint Paul taught the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13</note> ſaying, that there is no power but of God, &amp; that thoſe which doe reſiſt, reſiſt the ordinance of God. From thence it inſueth, that if anie one oppoſeth himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, when for the cauſe of religion hee would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the ſoueraigne princes which hee hath placed, and hath not called to the knowledge of him. Examine then this reaſon, whiles that Ipaſſe to the third point, which go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth altoge ther againſt thee, ſo good an aduocate art thou. Beholde how thou wouldeſt inferre, that becauſe it was forbidden to the Iſraelites, to admit anie heretike for their king, that the ſame ought to be ſayd and vnderſtood of all Chriſtian people.</p>
               <p>To the which I aunſwere, denying the propoſition and the illation together: beginning at the firſt, thou canſt not denie, but the moſt parte of the kings of Iuda and of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael, haue beene heretikes; as theyr idolatries and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſacrifices doe witneſſe, recited in theyr actes, the which kinges for all that, were not depoſed from theyr crownes. On the other ſide therefore, thou ſhalt bee conſtrayned to confeſſe, that the Chriſtians, much leſſe then ought to depoſe theyr kinges for cauſes of hereſie,
<note place="margin">Luk. 20. Rom. 13. Tit. 3</note> ſeeing that the commaundement of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles doe forbidde the ſame, as hath beene and ſhall bee ſeene.</p>
               <p>And for the fourth reaſon, I ſilie, that the king being a Chriſtian man, baptiſed and nouriſhed in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8747:7"/>Church, if hee doeth fall into ſome errour or defaulte, deſeruing a grieuous cenſure, ought not for the ſame cauſe to bee reputed as a ſtranger, whiles that hee maketh ſome profeſſion of the ſame religion, or whiles that hee witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his loue towardes the ſame, for the which cauſe Saint Paule ſpeaking of Excommunication, which hee calleth,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 9</note> marked by the Letter, ſayeth, Conuerſe not with him, to the end that hee may be aſhmed, neuertheleſſe hold him not as a common enemie, but rather admoniſh him as a brother. If thou oughteſt to doe this to the meaneſt in a realme, much more then to the ſoueraigne: in neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe ſuch a one as thou art? Finally, this lawe is quite contrarie to that of thine, when as thou doeſt hinder the waie which doeth eſtabliſh kings at this daie, as well approued of God, as the ancient lawe of the Iewes, the difference beeing onely in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde circumſtances, and not in the ſubſtaunce of the matter. From whence it proceedeth, that thou doeſt reſiſt the ordinance of God, when thou doeſt reiect him which hath right and calling to raigne ouer Fraunce, beeing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and receiued by the naturall and lawfull officers of the Crowne, hauing right and commaundement ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>To conclude, from the aforeſayd reaſons then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that this lawe of Moſes is not generall, but of old time particular to the Iewes. As in deede thou canſt not produce anie one example out from the primitiue church, thereby to ſaie, that that hath interpreted and vnderſtood this text ſo, ſeeing that that hath taught and practiſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together contrarilie. And as for that that thou addeſt, that the king hath bene condemned by the iudgement of the Church: it is anſwered, that one Biſhop of Italy, aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Romiſh Conſiſtorie, neither is, neither can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the vniuerſall Church, diſpearſed throughout the whole world.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:8747:8"/>
               <p>And furthermore, that hee of Rome can haue power no where, but in his owne dioceſſe, as the auncient Doctours doo witneſſe:
<note place="margin">Chap. 23</note> amongſt whom Baſile, in his booke, intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; The ſolitarie Life, ſayth, That all Biſhoppes doo binde and abſolue equally, as well as Peter. The ninth Canon of the councell of Antioch,
<note place="margin">Can. 9</note> carrieth as much, where it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid, that euerie Biſhop hath power and authoritie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his owne dioceſſe. The Romane Biſhop ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to content himſelfe with his owne at Rome, and not to vſurpe ouer all thoſe of France, where he hath nothing to doo, as hereafter more at large ſhall be diſcourſed and proued.</p>
               <p>Now I come to the other text, by the which thou doſt alleadge, that it is lawfull for thee to kill thy king, if thy credite could doo the ſame. It is expreſſed in the fiue and twentith of Numbers,
<note place="margin">Num. 25.</note> that the Lord commanded Moſes to take all the heades of the people, and hang them vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord agaynſt the Sunne, which had committed fornication and idolatrie with the Moabitiſh women: wherof thou doſt conclude, that the king ought to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as culpable of ſuch a crime. This is a leagued hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ſayth ſo, and I anſwere, that this example is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the matter, or to the purpoſe. Beholde therefore the ſupreame magiſtrate is not therby to be puniſhed, and much leſſe to be reiected. Secondarily, as well the diuines as the politicians, do affirme, that it is neither iuſt nor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, to vſe the ſame rigour, forme, and faſhion to a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Prince, beeing the lieuetenant of God, as is vſed to his ſubiects, (amongſt others) the example of Dauid ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth as a witneſſe. And in the third place, for to ſpeake the truth, ſuch principals of the people, haue not bene pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for the cauſe of hereſie, but rather and principally, for the cauſe of their fornication being qualified, euen as Saint Paul declareth to the Corinthians,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> where alledging this hiſtorie, he onely maketh mention of the aforeſayde
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8747:8"/>fornication, the which idolatrie hath not beene accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but as acceſſarie, ſeeing that the intention of theſe back-ſliders, was not to commit idolatrie, but onelie to commit fornication. Beholde then the allegation of this text is altogether from the matter, and verie fooliſhly and falſely applyed. Of the ſelfe ſame nature is the interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which thou giueſt, of that which followeth out of S.
<note place="margin">Math. 18</note> Matthew, where our ſauiour Chriſt would haue him hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for an heathen man, which will not obey the church, and alſo out of the which text thou draweſt the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. The anſwere is, that there he ſpeaketh of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and not of ſoueraigne magiſtrates. Secondly, of an ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall cenſure, and not of a politike. Thirdly, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken for a pagan, did not, nor yet doth take a waie the politike rightes of this world, which the Lorde giueth as well to princes as to their ſubiectes. The interpretation then which thou giueſt to this text, is altogether repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the intent of the ſpirite of God.
<note place="margin">Chro. 21</note> To this may bee applyed, ſayeſt thou, the example of the towne of Libna, belonging to the Leuites, which reuolted from king Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, becauſe of his idolatrie. Wherefore the holy hiſtorie ſayth, that he had forſaken the Lorde God of his fathers. To proue then, that ſuch an example is nothing at all to the matter, but rather tending to mutinie and rebellion, the reaſons are theſe. The king hath not forſaken the God of his fathers, and to proue that this is true, the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth deſcribe and propoſe the ſame God vnto vs, to be creator of all the world,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> &amp; the redeemer of them which beleeue in him and obey him, according as hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in his worde:
<note place="margin">Eph. 1.</note> they then which doo ſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this onely God of our fathers, Father of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11</note> by whom onely he hath reconciled the world to himſelf, following all the myſteries of our redemption,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5</note> which they ought to perfite and accompliſh in him the onely Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> Foraſmuch as there is no other name vnder
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8747:9"/>heauen by the which men may be ſaued. This father of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and of all faithfull Chriſtians, is the God of our fathers, as the heauenly oracles doe witnes vnto vs. Now the king beleeueth in him as ſuch a God, approueth him as ſuch a one, wherevppon it followeth, that hee hath not forſaken the God of our fathers. Secondly, thou oughteſt to know, that the contract of alliance betweene God and the Iewes, did more concern diuine religion, than humane policie. Wherfore there was ſuch a reciprocate ſubiection required betweene the kings of Iuda, and theyr ſubiectes, as a thing that was not elſe where. And for the laſt poynt, Ioram pretended to cauſe the people to commit idolatrie againſt God, the which our king would neuer do nor pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. Thou turneſt awaie then from this example, as alſo from the two following,
<note place="margin">1. King. 15. 2 King. 11.</note> of Maacah and Athalia, which thou doeſt aſſociate with him. And as for the firſt, let it be conſidered, that ſhe was a ſubiect, depoſed for idolatrie, and not a ſoueraigne, and that in the Country of Iuda. And as for the other, ſhe was a traitor, and an vniuſt vſurper of the crowne, which had maſſacred the two inheritours of the realme, and therefore was forſaken of thoſe which did belong vnto her, hauing the gouernment of the yong king Ioas. This was then the vniuſt vſurpation of a kingdome, that was the occaſion of this wicked womans death, and not hereſie. Heere ought I to ſpeake one worde, and one for all, of the pretended eloquence, but I will leaue it vnto the young Orators, and thoſe wicked wretches, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſhew vnto the world. Howſoeuer it bee, they care not, the ſmoakie ſtinking exhalations of the ſame, the which thou doeſt euaporate at all times, as well in this thy firſt Article, as alſo in thoſe that followe, thereby to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy Prince. Thou makeſt the qualitie of the veſſel, to be knowen by the ſtinking ſmell that commeth forth of it. The names ſignifie the things. I will content my ſelf to vſe ſimplicitie and ſinceritie, according to the property
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8747:9"/>of the truth, aduertiſing thee, that <hi>verba &amp; voces non leniunt dolorem.</hi> Wordes and voices do not aſſwage griefe. And by thy maieſticall &amp; iniurious ſpeeches, thou doeſtaccuſe the king to haue vſed many and diuers actes of hoſtilitie in the warres, which hee hath had heretofore. Vppon the which thou canſt not denie theſe two tryed truthes: the one, that he hath had a iuſt calling, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie occaſion to defende himſelfe againſt the forces of Guyfe his enemie: and the other, that hee hath by diuerſe ſufferances, and alterations (in compariſon) playd the part of an Angell, whileſt that they playd with him the part of a Deuill, vntill that time, that by ſuch proceedinges, you haue obiected againſt him, that hee hath vſed ſubtletie, to get aſwell the good opinion of one, as of another. But goe in one accorde your floutes, and let vs ſee the laſt poynt of of this Article, which is contained in the firſt to the Cor. where the Apoſtle doth reprehend the faithful Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6</note> which hauing matters of controuerſies amongſt them, go to plead them before Iudges, being Infidels, &amp; not among themſelues: ſhowing them, that it was euil done to ſubmit themſelues to the iudgment of Infidels, &amp; that they rather ought to take the leaſt amongſt them, &amp; appoint them for their Iudges. Wherupon this Ligall Doctor ſaith: that it is a very reprochfull thing to Catholickes to receiue him for king, which is now in the kingdome, the which he calleth (more outragiouſly than before) one that is falne a relapſe &amp; an Apoſtata fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Chriſtian religion: concluding that the Catholickes ought rather to chuſe the leaſt amongſt themſelues to bee theinking, than to ſubmitte themſelues vnder the yoke &amp; tyrannical gouernment of an Heretike. Thou ſaieſt all this. But if the heauens ſhould fall, what a noiſe would there be? Neuertheles yet let vs examine the fame. The agreement of the perſonages, as thou compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtable in one with another, doth prooue that the thing of it ſelfe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing at all alike, nor to the matter, for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8747:10"/>to compare the particular ſcandale which the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did giue in going to pleade their matters before hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Iudges, with the generall right due to Infidell Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? that doth nothing at all anihilate the obedience or dutie which Chriſtians doo owe them, as it appeareth by the ſame text, where Saint Paul doeth not permit the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians to digreſſe from their obedience for that cauſe? ſo farre off is he then from that that he commandeth in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. Kom. 13.</note> that praiers ſhoulde bee ordinarily made for them, and to honor them, and paie them tribute. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that becauſe the Apoſtle in this place doeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to take awaie the ſcandale which the Corinthians had giuen; it ſhould followe by the counſell of this vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable leaguer, that in ſtead of one ſhoulde ſpring mo then one hundred.</p>
               <p>But this is a knowen thing, that the deciding of a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wrong, hath no communitie with the generall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of a whole realme: for wee may well for our owne right or wrong, in giuing place to our ſelues, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede without ſcandale or ſedition: but the putting a king fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his kingdom can neuer be ſo done, and to be ſhort, the one is permitted, the other is forbidden, the one is in our power, the other not. Conſider then this ſottiſh faſhion of arguing. It is lawfull for mee in reſpecte of my buſineſſe, to chooſe him that I would, then is it lawfull for ſubiectes in renouncing theyr king, to chooſe ſuch a one as they thinke good, becauſe the other is not of theyr religion. This is well <hi>àſimili.</hi> I praie you what incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are there? What diuine or polititian woulde reaſon thus? Doeſt thou not ſee, that beſides this thy wickednes intaking a waie the ſeepter from him to whome the Lord hath giuen it, that it is not ſo eaſie a thing as thou doeſt make it, to rauine vp the pray from the lyon. Oh how thou wouldeſt bite and rend in peeces, if they counſell coulde attayne ſo much. Thou ſelleſt mans bloud good cheape.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:8747:10"/>
               <p>Alſo what Paradoxe is it, when as thou ſaieſt, that it were better to chuſe one of the moſte contemptibleſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Catholickes, and make him king? Doeſt thou not perceyue, that heere wee ought to reaſon of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Frenchman, beeing valiant, which will neuer practiſe the prouerbe, <hi>Ab equis ad aſinos;</hi> Out of the hall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kitchin. Furthermore, that ſuch a little king ſhoulde bee a poore vnaduiſed Icarus,
<note place="margin">Virg.</note> the which the heate of the ſunne in a moment, woulde cauſe to fall into the ſea. And not beeing therewith contente, to haue called the king an Ethnicke and Hereticke, but moreouer, thou nameſt him one that is fallen a relapſe, and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata. To the which thou haſt beene already ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye aunſwered elſe where, beſides that which by and by ſhall be added. It behooueth thee to proue, ſound, and examine the trueth of matters, and not falſly to deface the Magiſtrates giuen of God, by odious wordes, beeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented at pleaſure againſt thy conſcience. Behold the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to thy firſt Article, the which declareth thee to be a ſeditious ſlaunderer, and dooth cauſe thee to checke thy ſelfe of the faulte, the which thou doeſt falſly impute vnto thy king: for that, that it is hereſie to wreſt the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo as thou doeſt, in cauſing ſubiects to turne from the obedience which they owe vnto their ſoueraignes. And as for thoſe which do obiect, that the laſt kinges were not admitted to the crowne of France, but by the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Romiſh ceremonies, the which doe require (as ſome ſay) that the king that now raigneth, might enter in by the ſame gate: wee aunſwere, that ſuch ceremonyes ought not anyething at all to preiudice the diuine right, becauſe the neceſſitie doth preſent it ſelfe to reforme the Church. This beeing heere admitted of all true diuines, it ſhall alſo bee admitted, that it is not reaſonable, ſo bring kings in ſubiection to ſuperſtitions, beeing forbidden of God; and much leſſe to take away their politike admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8747:11"/>which God hath giuen them ouer kingdoms, for not obſeruing the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>The ſecond Article.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to the ſecond Article of this leagued Doctor, containing the Statutes &amp; Canons of the Councels: to the which, (to be of the ſame nature and dependencie) I will adde the ſeauenth, comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the decrees of the Pope. For theſe two Articles, by a common conſent do take in hand, to excommunicate the king as an heretike, with the nobles, &amp; others that follow him in quality, of fautors &amp; adherents of the hereſie. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is neceſſary to ſee, whether ſuch lightnings doe fall from heauen, as ſent from God, or whether they came out of the depth, as proceeded from Satan: &amp; to knowe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the children of light ought to feare them, or not. Let vs alſo be holde from the entraunce, whether this tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, throwing his tempeſtes againſt the king, doth ſhield himſelfe, as in former time, with the pretence of hereſie: which if he doth, we may annſwere him in like ſort as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how he ought to addreſſe himſelfe to a ſicke body: &amp; moreouer, that the remedie which he prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to giue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which might be holden of ſuch a malady, is peſtiferous &amp; mortall, and by conſequence not to be receiued: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhal anſwere to the names of ſuch ſpirituall mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, &amp; not maintaine the hereſie; (far off is it) but to ſhewe that the Biſhop of Rome, nor any other in the manner of ſpirituall Phiſitions, haue neither calling, right, mandate, or warrant, to depoſe infidell Princes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their kingdoms, ſcepters,
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> &amp; crownes which God hath giuen them, ſeeing the eccleſiaſtical cenſures ought to do nothing but in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual puniſhments concerning religion, &amp; not in politike cauſes of the world. To the which ends we wil thus argue againſt ſuch abuſes &amp; tyrannies. All that which is done in the church, for the cauſe &amp; right vſage of chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8747:11"/>ought to haue the worde of God for obiect &amp; foundation:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> for the authority of the ſame is altogether argued of in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity. But the Canons of ſuch Biſhops, &amp; the decrees of ſuch Popes, haue nothing for obiecte nor foundation, but only the corruptible wil &amp; inuentions of corruptible men; therfore it followeth, that ſuch Canons &amp; decrees do no; carrye themſelues to the right vſage of chriſtian religion. The Maior is proued by this generall maxime. A Biſhop can neither adde nor diminiſh to or from the holye ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<note place="margin">Deut. 4 1. Cor. 3.</note> for that it pronounceth a curſe againſt all men that ſhal take in hand to doe it, &amp; forbiddeth to laye any other foundation but him, which is already laide, that is to ſaye, Ieſus Chriſt. And like wiſe it ſhalbe ſaid to them that do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; who hath required theſe thinges at our handes?
<note place="margin">Eſa. 1</note> they are an abhomination vnto me. The Minor is thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; God commandeth to approue,
<note place="margin">Rom 13. 1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> acknowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect all kings, which he giueth to people of what religion ſoeuer they bee. From whence it followeth, that ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees &amp; Canons, doe oppoſe themſelues againſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: to the truth wherof theſe texts are witneſſe. And it ſhall come to paſſe,
<note place="margin">Ier. 27.</note> that the nation and kingdome which wil not ſerue Nabuchadnezer king of Babilon, ſhal be viſited, ſaith the Lorde. And in confirmation whereof, Ieſus Chriſt ſaith; giue to Caeſar that which is Caeſars then,
<note place="margin">Luk. 20.</note> although he was a Pagan, and thus is the Minor prooued. Againe, Iargue thus againſt the ſame Canons and decrees which do enterpriſe to diſplace Monarkes and kings, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Lordes. God onely is the authour and giuer of kingdoms; wherfore it followeth, that Popes and Biſhops haue no right to put them out: the antecedent is thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; produced by Ieremy. I haue made the earth, the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Iere. 27</note> &amp; the beaſts which are vpon the face of the earth, ſaith the Lord, &amp;c. I haue giuen to him to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath pleaſed me: now haue I giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the earth into the hands of Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezer king of Babylon, my ſeruant, all people ſhall ſerue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8747:12"/>him, and his ſonnes, and the ſonnes of his ſonnes. To the ſame ende the wiſe man did bring in God, ſpeaking thus: By mee kinges doe raigne:
<note place="margin">Prou. 8.</note> the conſequent is prooued in this ſort: No man hath right or commaundement to take away from any man that which he cannot giue, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath nothing to do: The Popes, Cardinals, &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, haue no right, nor any thing to do ouer kingdomes of the worlde: from them it followeth, that they haue no right to diſpoſſeſſe them, whereof theſe textes are witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note place="margin">Rom 13. Luk. 12.</note> that the powers are ordained of God. Giue to all them to whome it is due, tribute to whome tribute belongeth, and honor to whom honor is due.
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> The kings of the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do beare rule, but it ſhall not be ſo with you. Oh man, who hath appointed me iudge, &amp; a decider amongſt you? Marke, Chriſt whoſe wiſedome &amp; power was more great than that power of a million of millions of Popes, &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, would not then (although required) intermeddle with deciding betweene two brothers: Contrarily, the Pope, without beeing required in any thing, will by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, not onely iudge, but parte, diuide, and take awaye the kingdomes of the worlde, to tranſpoſe them where he liſt,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> imitating Satan when hee tempted Ieſus Chriſt, and would haue made him beleeue, that the kingdoms of the earth were at his diſpoſition, to giue them wher he ſhould thinke good. And I holde a third argument againſt ſuche Canons and decrees, vpon the calling, right, and nature of kinges, to whom (as to Soueraignes of kingdomes &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealthes) God hath ſubiected all other perſons,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> that do owe ſubiection, homage, obedience, tribute, and other like duties vnto them.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> So farre off is it then, that the kings (as theſe Canons would haue them) in ſuch ſort ſhould be tractable and puniſhable by the Miniſterie of Biſhoppes; whereas on the contrary, ſuch Miniſters (as their ſubiectes do owe to them all the foreſaid homages, euen to be them ſelues) not onely to bee diſgraded for default of this theyr
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8747:12"/>dutie, but alſo furthermore to bee puniſhed, according to the qualitie and quantitie of the faulte that they commit. Now then, that the kinges being ſoueraigne Magiſtrates, haue preheminence, dominion, and lordſhip generally o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all men of their kingdomes, of what condition ſoeuer they be,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> as appeareth by this generall commaundement of the Apoſtles, propoſed by word, diſtributiuely. All per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought to be ſubiect to their ſuperior powers: ſeeing then that the Biſhops are comprehended in the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, from thence it enſueth, not onely that they haue no right or power to depriue temporall Lordes of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and dignities; but that contrariwiſe, they ought to maintaine and defend them, euen to death if need be. Let ſuch Biſhops of Rome conſider therfore theſe things, and remember themſelues what Salomon ſaith;
<note place="margin">Prou. 19.</note> that it is not conuenient for the ſeruaunt to rule ouer Princes, and for the more celebrate commendations of them, the holye Scriptures doe adorne them with the titles of diuinitie.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> When then the Biſhop, in ſtead of reuerencing and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his king, doth lift himſelfe vp againſt his Maieſtie, he committeth two other abhominable faultes. The firſt is, where he detaineth vniuſtly that which he oweth to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The ſecond is, that hee is a rebell, traitour, and felon, in lifting vp himſelfe againſt his Lorde, to whom hee is in ſubiection by the lawes of God and nature. The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is then, that a Biſhop (yea were it the Biſhop of Rome, vndertaking to deſtroy and ouerthrow the ſtate of a king) is worthie to be hanged. S. Iude ſpeaking of ſuch people,
<note place="margin">S. Iude in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> epiſt.</note> ſayth, that the obſcuritie of darkneſſe is prepared for them. And heere it will not ſerue ſufficiently for him, to arme himſelfe with a pretence of a Romiſh preheminence, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it hath no proppe nor foundation in the Scripture. Let the greateſt amongſt you be as the leaſt (ſaith our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt) it was not ſo from the beginning.
<note place="margin">Luk. 12. Mat. 19.</note> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties and abſurdities which are founde in the Canons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8747:13"/>and decrees of the Popes doe witneſſe ſufficiently, with what ſpirite they doe proceede, and doe ſhewe what cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and authoritie ought to bee giuen to them. Petrarke, who as one that had more knowledge, than anye of his time, did call Rome the hell of the liuing, and the priſon of wrath. Notwithſtanding theſe leaguers woulde make vs beleeue, that when ſuch Biſhops ſhal commit the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt enormious faultes of the worlde, ſuch as are their conſpiracies againſt the ſoueraigne magiſtrates, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and appoynted of God, that they are mooued by the heauenly inſpiration. The wiſe king may heere conſider to whome it doth appertaine to deſtroye the councell of the wicked,
<note place="margin">Prou. 20.</note> as Salomon ſayth: to turne the wheele vpon them. God puniſheth ſuch when it ſeemeth him good. It is verie true, that the not puniſhing of theſe kinde of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, proceeding from the ignoraunce and negligence of the ſoueraigne Magiſtrates, is the occaſion that theſe doe giue themſelues leaue continually to do like faults, hoping that it will be alwayes with them as with harlottes,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> which perſwade themſelues of no puniſhment, for that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes keepe themſelues in Townes or publike Stewes of the common-wealth, thinking that they are not only tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, but alſo to bee maintained as thoſe of Rome. But if this iniurious time cauſeth that there is not founde a Magiſtrate at this daye in the earth, which dooth repaye ſuche by Iuſtice, when as they manifeſt themſelues to bee ſeditious, trayterous, ſchiſmatickes, heretikes, murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Sodomites, Magitians, and Atheiſtes, the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of God in the time appoynted can verie well pay the intereſt of ſuch attentions and dilations. This is heere ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon the more than diueliſh ſawcines of the Biſhops of Rome,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> the which by decrees and Canons, as Giantes, doe take in hande, contrary to the ordinance of God, not only to diſgrade, but alſo to kill and exterminate the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the earth.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:8747:13"/>
               <p>This is no meruaile then, ſeeing the Pope challengeth power alſo ouer the Angelles. Let vs continue the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of this Article. The Author addeth (by exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and parentheſis) that for the cauſe of hereſie, ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons doe diſgrade euen to the Pope, deſiring to affirme, notwithſtanding that hee is erected aboue all Monarkes of the earth. What greate admiration is this? as if it were not knowne, that all men receyuing a charge of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, receyueth it with condition to bee depoſed. If hee becommeth an heretike, the word of God doth declare it manifeſtly: and the euill is, that in thy place the practiſe doth oppoſe it ſelfe. Admit this; yet it is denied that hee may take in like manner fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kings of the earth,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> becauſe that amongſt other thinges their charge is different from the eccleſiaſtical, &amp; becauſe they haue receiued their poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike adminiſtration without ſuch condition. But if it doth fall out, that a prince ſhould be cenſured touching the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing him of the goods &amp; honors of this world, it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to a politike conuocation of eſtates, &amp; not to eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical perſons. And proceeding, the Monke addeth, that theſe Canons do abſolue &amp; releaſe all ſubiectes, from the obedience that they owe to their Lordes or kinges, being heretikes. Now for the anſwer: It hath been ſaid &amp; proued againſt ſuch iniuſtice, that God raigneth ouer kingdoms, &amp; eſtabliſheth thoſe whom he pleaſeth, be they faithful or infidels. I haue called thee, ſaith the lord to Cirus,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 45.</note> although thou haſt not knowne me, and I haue named thee by this name, to the ende to make the nations ſubiect vnto thee. This is here ſaide of Pagan princes. Now let vs enter into the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-welth of Iſrael, where the church of God was, and where all the kings ought to haue made profeſſion of the true religion. There were found many heretikes before and after their comming to the kingdom, neuertheles not one of them was euer depoſed for hereſie. To bee ſhorte, neither the Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, haue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8747:14"/>euer taken away,
<note place="margin">Ier. 27. Luk. 20. Rom. 13.</note> or aboliſhed the dignities and pollicies of the world for ſuch reſpects: but rather haue maintained and confirmed ſuch magiſtrates, in commaunding to giue to Pagan Princes the things which God hath ordained &amp; aſſigned for them. Heere thou doeſt reply, that ſeeing that we ought rather to obey the creator, than the creature; if it commeth to paſſe, that the ſeruice of the king doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract vs from the ſeruice of God: wee ought to leaue the leſſe, to obey the greater. The anſwere is, that this maxime is verefied in it ſelfe, but very badly applyed to that which is the queſtion, beeing conſidered, that they doe obey the creator which do obey his commaundements, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their dueties which they owe vnto their ſoueraigne Magiſtrate. And if for the cauſe of religion he would draw thee from the ſeruice of God, then the Prophets, Ieſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, commaund thee not to digreſſe from it (ſo farre off is it that thou ſhouldſt roote him out) that contrariwiſe thou oughteſt to pray to God for him, becauſe hee hath the hearts of Princes in his handes: and otherwiſe,
<note place="margin">Prou. 21. Math. 10.</note> they commaund thee to endure perſecution, or to flie and go ſome where elſe. If theſe be not thy procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, thou art no diſciple of Chriſt. Let vs ſee how thou doeſt borrow the examples following.</p>
               <p>The firſt is of the bande of wiues towardes their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes. The ſecond is, of children towardes their fathers. The third is, of ſeruantes towardes their maiſters. Where thou ſaieſt that in the caſe of hereſie ſuch bands do ceaſe: and from thence thou doſt inferre, that for the ſame cauſe the band of the ſubiectes towardes their Princes ought to ceaſe. Now for aunſwere I ſay, that the antecedent is falſe, and that the conſequence is not true. Beginning at the firſt example, thou doeſt alleadge and apply falſly; for the text ſayth word for word: That if any woman hath married an infidell, and if hee is content to dwell with her, let her not depart from him.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.</note> Where it is added, what knoweſt thou
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8747:14"/>woman, whether thou ſhalt ſaue thy husband, or not? that is to ſay, by praiers, inſtructions, and good conuerſations. It is well ſayd in the text, that if the infidell or vnbeleeuer will departe, let him departe: But ſuch a ſeperation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not from the beleeuer, but from the vnbeleeuing. Behold how thou doeſt falſly alleadge the worde of God. And in reſpect of the ſecond example, all men know, that amongſt the dueties of the worlde, the obedience of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren towards their fathers, be they beleeuers or vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, is ſo generally and profoundly imprinted in the breſt of mankinde, that aſwell the lawes diuine as humane, doe commaund it alwayes without exception, ſo clearely, that to dilate theſe thinges by examples and textes, is to ſowe nothing elſe but wordes of wiſedome in vaine.
<note place="margin">Terent.</note> A Pagan would aunſwere that nature could not breake this duetie. If ſome of your Canons haue giuen him ſuch great autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as thou talkeſt of, it may bee aunſwered, that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of them were worſe than infidelles. And as for the third example taken from ſlaues,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> which may in caſe of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie (ſaieſt thou) in like ſorte abandon theyr maiſters. To aunſwere that, Saint Paule the Doctor of the Gentils, doth tell thee that thou doeſt lye, when hee commaunded ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes in his time to obey theyr Maiſters, which were for the moſt part infidels, ſaying: Seruants,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. Gen. 14.</note> obey them which are your Maiſters, according to the fleſh; for ſo Ioſeph was obedient vnto Pharao, and alſo to his firſt Maiſter: and Abdias to Achab his Lorde, which was an heretike,
<note place="margin">1. King. 28.</note> and moreouer an hypocrite, and a perſecutour of the Church.</p>
               <p>If then becauſe of religion, priuate men maye not leeſe their right which they haue ouer their ſeruants: much leſſe then ſhoulde Monarkes leeſe the obedience and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement which is due vnto them, from thoſe whom the Lorde hath ſubiected vnto them, by diuine and humane right: otherwiſe I pray you, what maner of arguing wold
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8747:15"/>this be, if a prince diſobeyeth God in a pointe of religion, then it is permitted to take his ſcepter from him.</p>
               <p>Now I muſt enter into the great denth of the Romiſh excommunication, by the Miniſterie whereof this leaguer doth pretend to curſe and roote out, aſwell the king, as the nobles, and other ſubiects which do take his part. He ſaith then, that if a prince be excommunicated, the Canons doe forbid, that any obedience ſhould be giuen vnto him. And comming from theſe to Hypotheſe, he produceth the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of excommunication of Pope Sixtus the fifth of that name, denounced againſt the king, in the yeare 1585. the ninth of September, beginning thus: we do eſtabliſh in the full power which the king of kinges hath giuen vs, &amp;c. in the which are compriſed the nobles, and other Catholicks which do helpe the king, as fauters of heretikes. To anſwer the ſame, and for the more briefe and eaſie vnderſtanding of this matter of excommunication, it is requiſite to diuide it into foure parts. The definition of the thing ſhall be the firſt. The ſecond ſhall comprehend the authoritie and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thoſe who ought to excommunicate. The thirde ſhall haue regarde to the qualitie of the crime, together with the ende of the cenſure. The fourth ſhall intreate of the commodities and rightes of this preſent life, to knowe whether eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction hath power to depoſe them from their proper rights or not. The worde Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication is defined in this manner.</p>
               <p>Excommunication is a banniſhment or reiecting of an obſtinate ſinner, beeing hardened in his ſinne, the which is throwne out of the company of the faithful, by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſentence of the Church, by the authoritie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: following the rule which is contained in hys worde. The which eccleſiaſticall puniſhment is ordained as well to cauſe the ſinner to repent and amende, as alſo for the edification of the foreſaide Church. The ſeconde parte, is touching the perſons which ought to pronounce
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8747:15"/>ſuch ſentence of excommunication, for if it be proffered &amp; done by a man hauing no calling, it is nothing, like as a band made without forme of lawe.</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary therefore to knowe in generall, that the power of excommunication is giuen to the church, as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt doth witneſſe in the Goſpell written by S. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,
<note place="margin">Mat. 19.</note> where ſpeaking of him that will neither hear in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, nor in the preſence of one or two witneſſes: his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which then hath offended, commaundeth the partie offended, to tell ſuch his rebellion to the Church, as to the which the iudgement and acknowledgement of the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which falleth to him that hath offended, doth belong. After the Maiſter, Saint Paule his Diſciple ſpeaketh thus of the proceeding of excommunication holden agaynſt the inceſtuous Corinthians.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> I haue determined (ſaith he) as being preſent, that he which hath done this thing, be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered &amp;c. And afterwards adding (you and my ſpirit being aſſembled with you in the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt) to deliuer (I ſay) ſuch a man to Satan, for the deſtruction of the fleſh, to the end that the ſpirit may be ſaued in the day of our Lord.</p>
               <p>It may be ſeene then, that this iudgement is deferred to the Church, which chuſeth a certayne number of men, to the which ſhee giueth charge to watch ouer the flockes, and to haue certaine knowledge of him which hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to bring him backe againe to the trueth, to the ende that if there doe fall out the cenſure of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it maye bee doone by the ſight and agreement of the Church,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note> according to the authoritie which Ieſus Chriſt hath giuen her. This is then a certaine token, that the obſtinate ſinner ought to be excommunicated in the ſame Church, whereof hee is a member, and in the which the fault hath beene committed to her greate offence. And becauſe that excommunication is the laſt and moſte ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere eccleſiaſticall cenſure againſt the ſinner, therefore it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8747:16"/>is good to proceede in all thinges deliberately, by good counſaile,
<note place="margin">Epiſt. lib. 3. Epiſt. 19.</note> and manifeſt proofe of the cauſe. Wherefore S. Cyprian ſayth, that the Biſhops of his time, did call the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops of their prouinces, when there was any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of excommunicating the rebellious and obſtinate. Where it appeareth, that there is found no ſuch matter, as in the Romiſh proceedinges: ſeeing that they excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate not onely thoſe which be not of their dioceſſe, but all other out of their prouinces, as they thinke good: ouer the which they haue no more to do, than this my leagued Monke hath ouer the Tartarians. This abuſe doth aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate it ſelfe the more, in as much as the Popes beeing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of manye crimes, doe notwithſtanding iudge them which are their accuſers: where we may not omit, that of old time our Fathers did ordaine and appoint thoſe things which they thought conuenient, profitable, and neceſſary for the correction of thoſe which did belong vnto the French Church, without going into Italie a as is prooued and ſhewed amongſt others, by the authour of the abuſes and nullities of the Bulles of Pope Sixtus that dyed laſt: the which dooth ſhewe by many examples,
<note place="margin">Aim. lib. 5. cap. 26.</note> that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Fraunce, warned Pope Gregorie the fourth, which came into the Realme with menaces of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications to the king, that if hee did enterpriſe any thing againſt him, in ſteade to excommunicate, hee ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne excommunicated. Likewiſe it was tolde him, that it was neuer ſeene, that a Pope not being deſired, ſhould euer meddle with iudging the rightes belonging to king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and that the Frenchmen had alwayes accuſtomed to liue in libertie: for the maintenance of the which, they were reſolued not to ſpare their owne bloud. And laſtly, they tolde him that kingdomes were neuer gotten by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications.</p>
               <p>From all which reaſons it followeth, that the French men haue no reaſon to ſeare the Popes encommunications. If
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8747:16"/>it falleth out, that anie of them do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit anie offence, they may go to the Biſhops of Fraunce, which ought to reduce them by faire meanes, &amp; cenſure them accordingly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuffering them to go to Rome. And for the third parte of the excommunication, touching the perſon excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, together with the ende of ſuch cenſuring: Firſt I ſayde, that it is neceſſary to admoniſh the culpable by all faire meanes, euen with teares, as alſo to heare and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him in all his reaſons, plaintes, and iuſtifications, to knowe thereby whether he bee duely informed of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, or not. Now there hath beene no ſuch obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the foreſaide ſentence of excommunication; from thence therefore againe it followeth, that it is not onely a nullitie, but alſo a deteſtable abuſe. That which doth alſo againe appeare for the third, is the qualitie of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded crime of hereſie, wherewith the Pope accuſeth the king; foraſmuch as it is verefied, that ſuche a propoſition (the Romane Church hath neede of reformation) is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all erronious, and much leſſe hereticall. Lette vs now behold the end of excommunication. It hath beene ſayd, that it hath reſpect vnto the repentance and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſinner: wherefore I deſire all that be truly religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to confider whether the Pope indeuoreth himſelfe to this ende, when he excommunicateth kinges: they ſhall find that he doth not. Beholde, let a Prince bee a tyraunt, a whoremaiſter, adulterous, a rauiſher, a drunkard, a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph emer, and an Atheiſt, doing as much of theſe thinges as he will, yea although hee bee quallified with all ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, yet the Pope will not once deigne to tell him of the leaſt of them, no not to his Biſhops, ſo farre off is hee from ſpeaking of the excommunicating, either of the one, or the other, for ſuch reſpects reſeruing the thunderbolts and threatninges of the ſame, onely againſt thoſe which doe talke of the abuſes and wickednes of the ſame, and of the way how to hinder that courſe. Now the fourth parte of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8747:17"/>the diuiſion remaineth yet to be looked into, which is as much to ſaie, whether by the miniſtrie of the excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, the Biſhops of Rome may depriue Monarches of the benefites and rightes of this preſent life or not; for proofe to the contrarie,
<note place="margin">Luk. 20. Rom. 13</note> it hath bene already ſayd and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that God hauing giuen the Empires and kingdomes of the world, to thoſe whom he hath choſen from amongſt men, doth forbid all Biſhoppes, Cardinalles, Monkes, and Prieſts, to diſturbe or depriue them of the ſame. If the Princes be wiſe, they haue tallans good inough to defend themſelues from ſuch iniuries, if they doo not make them their owne hurt. This iniquitie of the Biſhopps of Rome, (which vnder the pretence of eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction do tranſpoſe kingdomes to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wil) ſhal better appeare by the conferring of the eccleſiaſticall gouernment with the politike, which we will alſo handle. Firſt of all, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Church is ſpirituall, and that of the Magiſtrates is corporall. Secondly, the Church iudgeth according to the diuine lawes of the word of God, and the Magiſtrate politikely, according to the courſe of the worlde. Thirdly, the Church doth puniſh the rebellious ſpiritually in the ſoules with eccleſiaſticall paines, and the Magiſtrates cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally in the fleſh with politike pains, ouer the which the Church hath nothing to do. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it foloweth, that if it ſhould be ſuch a maner of excommunication, then the eccleſiaſticall perſons haue nothing to do with the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goods of priuate men, &amp; much leſſe with realmes, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Empires. By this conference, the moſt block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh amongſt the Antipodes, may eaſily indge of ſuch abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, much more then the French men. If for wilfulneſſe of heart they doe not picke out their eyes, ſo that they maye not ſee at noone time, when as the Sunne is in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: aſſure your ſelues then, my maiſters, that all excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> beeing abuſed, cannot ſhut the gates of paradiſe agaynſt you, ſeeing that God doeth keepe them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8747:17"/>open for all louers of godlyneſſe and truth, in deſpight of him which ſayth, that hee hath power to ſhutte them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, for which cauſe it is ſayde in the Prouerbes, that the curſing without cauſe will neuer come to paſſe.
<note place="margin">Prou. 26.</note> To conclude, the Apoſtles did not care for the excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of the Scribes and Phareſies: much leſſe then ought the French men to care for the Italian or Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh eſtate, becauſe they haue leſſe to doe with them, than the aforeſayde Scribes and Phareſies had to doo with the Diſciples of our ſauiour Chriſt. Heere muſt not bee forgotten the titles and qualities which the Biſhop of Rome doth attribute to himſelfe,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> when as he nameth him ſelfe chiefe and ſoueraigne paſtor of the Church, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed (ſayth hee) in the full power of the king of kings, and of Saint Peter and Saint Paule, and of his owne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, with his Cardinalles. And I praie you what to doe? Onely to root out, and excommunicate, if he could, Henrie of Bourbon, at this daie our king of France, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of his ſentence. In the which wee finde a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a pride more than deuilliſh, for the holy ſcriptures doe witneſſe, that theſe diuine titles, Chiefe ſoueraigne, and ſoueraigne paſtor of the Church, doe appertayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, God bee bleſſed for euer, who onely is called chiefe of the Church, by Saint Paule,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.4 Col. 1.2</note> writing to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, in the firſt and fourth Chapters, and vnto the Coloſſians, in the firſt and ſecond Chapters. This is alſo hee alone which is called by Saint Peter,
<note place="margin">1. Pet 5</note> in his firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and fifth Chapter, the chiefe ſhepheard of our ſoules, and in the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, and eighth Chapter,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8</note> is called the ſoueraigne ſacrificer. Theſe two Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles (whoſe ſucceſſours the Biſhoppes of Rome doe call themſelues,) they haue great regard, not to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to themſelues ſuch titles of diuinitie, knowing that they doe belong to none, but onely to Chriſt, being onely iuſt; thereby to diſtinguiſh him from the vniuſt, therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8747:18"/>they ſpeake ſimply of themſelues in this ſort. I deſire the Elders ſaith S.
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 1. Cor. 4.</note> Peter, which am alſo an Elder with them. And S. Paule ſayth, let men eſteeme of vs, as of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2</note> Hee ſaith in the ſecond epiſtle written to the Theſſalonians, that it belongeth to the ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to attribute vnto himſelfe ſuch diuine titles. The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church doth alſo giue the lie to the ambitious prieſt of Rome. In witnes whereof, amongſt other, the Canon of the third Councell of Carthage ſayth,
<note place="margin">Cap. 1 ſed diſt. 99.</note> that the Biſhoppe of the firſt ſea, was not called prince of prieſts, nor ſoueraign prieſt,
<note place="margin">Tom. 7. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 43. in Mat. ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. li 7. c. 30</note> or ſuch like: and that hee cannot call himſelfe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall. Chriſoſtome ſpeaking of all Biſhoppes, ſayth thus. Whoſoeuer ſhall deſire the primacie on earth, ſhall not be numbred amongſt the diſciples of Chriſt. Finally, all men knowe, that Gregory hath beene a capitall enemie to this title of vniuerſall Biſhop, ſo farre foorth, that by the ſame hee ſayth, that hee did perceyue the nigh comming of Antichriſt. Wherefore hee concludeth, that ſuche a title is prophane, and that ſuche tytles doe declare vnto vs the inſupportable pride of ſuch a Biſhop, ſo doeth the vantage of hauing full power (as Sathan ſaith of himſelfe) ouer the kingdomes of the earth (giuing the lie to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Daniel) which attributeth it to one onely God.
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 5</note> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe I doo agree moſt willingly to this truth, that the Pope is alſo eſtabliſhed in the full power, as wel of him ſelfe, as of his Cardinals. Let vs nowe ende the reſt of this Article. This leagall Proctor, willing to let nothing paſſe that might ſerue him towards the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of his king, hath ſhewed foorth yet another certaine Canon of Lutheran, ordeining, that kings ſhal neuer come to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, vntill they haue firſt ſworne to defend the Romane Catholike religion. It hath bin anſwered, vpon the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie of their Canons, that the eccleſiaſticall perſons, bee it in their councels, or bee it in their conſiſtories, or elſe where, haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, right, nor calling, to driue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8747:18"/>kings from their kingdomes and Lordſhips, which it hath pleaſed God to giue them, ſeeing that he will rather ſerue himſelfe with the miniſterie of them in ſuch adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than of others.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, we ſaie, that the intention of the king, is to maintaine the puritie and truth of the Catholike, Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and Chriſtian religion, with as good an affection as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other king that euer raigned in France. He hath vowed it, and the experience will followe, (God helping) to the contentment of al true religious Chriſtians. And as for the Romane, his intention is nothing elſe, but to let euery one looſe to his owne libertie: Holding it for a Maxime, that by the examples of Chriſt, and his Apoſties,
<note place="margin">Math. 11 Act. 13 Kom. 10</note> one neyther can nor may bring men to the beleefe of the Goſpell by force, ſeeing that that appertayneth to one onely God, to touch and moue the heartes, cauſing them to beleeue to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Let vs adde, that by a free and amiable conference, that all that which ſhall bee found good and conformable to the word of God in the Romane Church, ſhall bee rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, confirmed, and approued. What is it then that thou doeſt require more of a faithfull Prince towardes the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion? If not a reprehenſion agreeable to ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiues, which impudently thou doeſt produce agaynſt his maieſtie. Thou giueſt vs afterwardes a gradation of of hereſies, touching the reformation of the Church, brought into Fraunce, the which thou calleſt the hereſie of Caluin, more deteſtable then all the reſt. To the which is aunſwered, that it hath beene ſufficiently maintayned and proued, that the Church of Rome doeth erre in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pointes of doctrine, and that it hath neede of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
               <p>Heereupon it is come to paſſe, that many haue renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced her errors, idolatries, and ſuperſtitions, to follow chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, according to the firſt inſtitution, purity, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8747:19"/>and ſinceritie. You call this reformation, hereſie. But if in deede in naming good euill. All thoſe which will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen theyr eyes, may ſee this neceſſitie a farre off. If there were neede to giue place to thy inductions and gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I would produce two, the truth whereof thou canſt not denie.</p>
               <p>And the firſt is, that at Rome hath beene made ſuch an aſſemblie of idolatries,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2</note> errours, and ſuperſtitions, that they doe iuſtifie the religion of Presbiter Iohn, and of the Muſcouite. The other alſo ſhould be; that the Biſhop of the ſame towne, mounting from degree to degree, is placed in the moſt abhominable ſcate of all Europe. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they are alreadie verified &amp; proued by thoſe which thou canſt not contradict.</p>
               <p>Now then it remaineth, after the counterbatterie of thy Eccleſiaſticall Canons, to repulſe the application and interpretation, which thou giueſt to certaine imperyall lawes, which condemne the heretikes in diuerſe paines, as by banniſhment, confiſcation of goods, and other ſuch like. From whence thou draweſt then this concluſion, that the king ought not onely ſo to bee handled, but alſo to be put to death. Theſe are thy proper tearmes, when thou ſayeſt, If ye will haue the lawes ſtand in force, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie that the heretike ſhould die. And for want whereof the ſtate of France is more miſerable, than the pollicie of theeues. To all that hath beene alreadie aunſwered, firſt, that the ſoueraigne gouernours are not to bee compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the like rigor of ciuill puniſhments, as their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects are, for the reaſons that wee haue alleadged elſe where.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that ſuch heretikes were puniſhed, ſome for hereſies being qualified, which did turne vp ſide down the foundation of Chriſtian religion, beeing knowen and approued ſuch, by the true Doctours of the Church. And for the laſt, ſo farre off is it, that thou mayeſt ſaie ſo of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8747:19"/>king, that contrarie-wiſe it hath beene prooued, that if there bee anie Prince in the worlde farre from hereſie, and from anie opinion, that may anie kinde of wale ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch it, it is hee, ſeeing that he followeth Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the greateſt meaſure of reformation of the ſame, as euer hath bene ſithence the death of the Apoſtles. Moſt truely therefore I conclude, that in curſing the king, lyke to another Semei, and condemning of him to death, by the examples of Caiphas,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> thou doeſt demerite meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the condemnation of two. And as for the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, importing, that for not killing of the king, the aboue ſayde inconueniences woulde come to paſſe. It may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be anſwered, that in killing the king giuen of GOD for the gouernment of the people of France, ſhoulde bee committed the moſt great and hainous ſinne of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond table of the Lawe, by the which notable wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, the wrath and vengeance of God ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked.</p>
               <p>And to conclude, it is neceſſarie to ſhew thee a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errour, vpon the ending of the two Articles, within the which thou doeſt inwarp all thy ſpeech, and this it is, that thou doeſt alwaies inferre in thy Arguments, that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie is a greater ſinne than all other infidelitie, ſuch as are Paganiſme, Atheiſme, Idolatrie, and generally all other defection from God and his religion. The contrarie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by theſe argumentes. Hee that denieth the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt quantitie of truth, is a greater lyar, than hee which denyeth the leſſe. Such therefore bee the Pagans, which doe denie altogether all the truth of Chriſtian religion, wherefore it followeth, that they are greater liers, and more to bee condemned, chan the heretikes which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie leſſe.</p>
               <p>And agayne, Euerie man (ſuch as is the Atheiſt, which denyeth the eſſence of GOD, and his effects, is more abhominable than he which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth the one &amp; the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8747:20"/>other, from whence it proceedeth, that Atheiſts are worſe than heretiks. To the like effect or end, I thus argue. Thoſe which doo generally abiure from the true God and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, are worſe than thoſe which doe but in parte, from whence yet it followeth, that ſuch deſtroyers are worſe than heretikes. As in deede ſuch Infidelles are altogether ſtraungers from the common weale of Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 2</note> the which cannot bee ſaid of the heretike, which ſhall beleeue in one God, the contentes of his worde, and the truth of his promiſes, failing onely in this point, that hee doth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſome Articles and texts of holy Scripture amiſſe. If thou doeſt obiect, that many heretikes haue maliciouſſie and againſt their conſciences, ſtriuen againſt the truth, I anſwere, that in ſuch a caſe mans iudgement ceaſeth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God alone can examine and ſound the heartes of men:
<note place="margin">Iere. 20.</note> otherwiſe, to ſaie the truth, if they come to that point they ought not to be called heretikes, but Apoſtatates and arch-enemies of God, the which by conſequence, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the example of one Iulian, ſhould ſinne againſt the holy ſpirit. Poſſibly Arrius did the like. That beeing taken awaie, it is neceſſarie to obſerue all ſuch diſtinctions, for feare of enwrapping them in the ſame condemnation which doe erre by ſimple ignorance. What ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the moſt part of the ancient doctors, if they were admitted? We doe not onely then ſaie, that there is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene Apoſtaſie and hereſie, but alſo between hereſie and hereſie, and moreouer all errour is not he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, if it be demaunded into what predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſimple heretikes may or ought to bee put, and what iudgement is to bee giuen of them. I aunſwere, that they ought to be handled more fauourablie than thoſe which are excommunicated: the reaſon wherof (amongſt others is this, that becauſe they are not banniſhed nor reiected of the Church, and becauſe they haue neuer done any acts of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8747:20"/>rebellion or contempts, as the aforeſaid excommunicated haue: Concerning the which neuertheles, it is ſaide,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> that they are deliuered to Satan, for the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh: to the ende that their ſoules may bee ſaued in the daye of the Lord. Seeing then that excommunication doth not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude theſe heere from the hope of ſaluation, much leſſe then the heretikes, ſeeing they are leſſe withdrawing from the way of repentance, than the excommunicates. Nowe to ſhew that all thoſe which do erre in ſome poynt of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, are not ſo foule as this leaguer doth make them; wee will produce two examples drawne from the worde of God.</p>
               <p>The Corinthians did erre in one of the moſt principall articles of the chriſtian fayth, in denying the reſurrection of the body, a quallified hereſie, if there were euer any, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it did aboliſh (as S. Paule prooueth) the whole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the death and paſſion of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> Let vs come to S. Peter, who beeing better inſtructed than the faythfull Corinthians, miſtaking an Article of the Chriſtian liberty, and beeing vnknowne, fell into a poynt of hereſie: becauſe that after the death of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> he thought it to bee a pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule and conſcience, to eat of all ſorts of meat, as if in ſuch, an abſtinence did conſiſt in a part of ſaluation for mankind, quite contrary to that which S.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> Paule dooth teach, when he ſayth, that God had created meates, to the end that the faithfull which haue knowne the truth, maye vſe them with giuing of thanks. Behold then heere a body of the Church, and an Apoſtle, heretikes euery one of them in a point of hereſie. Neuertheleſſe they were not reiected of the church, nor depoſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their charges for the ſame. Yea ſuch opinions were not imputed vnto them for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, becauſe there was no obſtinacie in them, nor a wicked purpoſe to reſiſt circumſtances, requiſite for a formall he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. Euen as the auncient Doctors haue noted, aſwell as the Schoolmen, affirming, that he is no heretike, that doth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8747:21"/>ſimply erre, if there commeth not a wicked purpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, and an obſtinacie to ſtriue and ſtand againſt the trueth. To the which promiſe is alleadged that which S. Auguſtine ſayth; I may erre, but I will not be an heretike. If theſe conſiderations doe purge as well the Church of Corinth, as an Apoſtle, why not then alſo a king, when as he doth but onely ſay, that the Romane Church doth erre in certaine points? A propoſition which hath leſſe cauſe to be charged with hereſie than the former. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, let vs graunt ſuch a propoſition (the Romane church hath neede of reformation) be erroneous, we may aunſwer as before. That for not beeing ſet forwarde, with willing purpoſe of the heart, to the end to ſtand againſt the trueth, it ought not to be imputed hereſie. If thou doeſt replye, that it is vppon mallice and obſtinacie, that the king doth maintaine ſuche a propoſition: I will aunſwere thee as I haue doone elſewhere, returning thither; Who will bee ſo wicked to ſay, that the king doth intermeddle, or hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedled, and with a malitious will againſt his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the cauſe of religion? What profit could come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by the ſame? Leauing then this frenzines vnwoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy any aunſwere, I will paſſe to the thirde Article, vppon the which wee neede no more to inſiſt, than in the others going before, foraſmuch as the generall and neceſſary an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weres to this ſubiect haue beene already produced, which will helpe the ſolution of the Articles following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>The third Article.</head>
               <p>THe third Article commeth to this poynte, that the Catholickes which doe accompany the king, doe breake the naturall law in the acte of religion, that which the barbarous nations neuer did. For this confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and commendation of which Article, this author al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgeth diuers examples drawne out of the Pagans ſhop,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8747:21"/>from whence hee conoludeth, that ſuch Catholickes are worſe than they, becauſe they accompany a king that is not of their religion. Therein is contayned two poyntes: The firſt reſteth in the knowledge and propertie of the law of nature, in the which is the queſtion: The ſecond in the nature and force of the examples. Therfore we ought firſt to know, what it is to ſay the naturall law in matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. To this purpoſe therfore S. Paule ſayth,
<note place="margin">1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man doth not comprehend the things of the ſpirite of God, becauſe they are vnto him as fooliſhnes, &amp; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderſtand them. Wherupon it followeth, that for the vnderſtanding of them, he ought to be otherwiſe than na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall: that is to ſay,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 5</note> that he ought to haue ſome thing from aboue, &amp; beyond the gifts of the humane ſoul. That which in other places the ſame Apoſtle calleth the ſpirit of reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: and the eye of the vnderſtanding being inlightned. Much more then the naturall man will affecte his naturall religion, which is not but of the world, &amp; therfore the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the true ordinance of God, conſidering that it is fooliſhnes vnto him, &amp; ſo conſequently can neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it, if the ſupernaturall gifts of the holy ſpirite doe not come between. From whence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that to imbrace the true religion, being ſupernatural, he ought rather to go againſt the law of nature, than to followe the courſe and conduction of the ſame. It appeareth then, that thou doeſt very badly apply thy naturall lawe in the caſe of religion. But if thou doeſt reply that by the lawe of nature thou doeſt vnderſtand an inſeperation and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be borne &amp; nouriſhed together with man, tending to the good and preſeruation of mans life. Vppon ſuch an interpretation, thou doeſt ſhew thy ſelfe without compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon to be a greater tranſgreſſer of this lawe, than thoſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon whom thou doeſt falſely impoſe ſuch a crime. Behold the law of nature requireth, that one ſhould be gentle and tractable towards his countriman.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:8747:22"/>
               <p>Which doth demonſtrate amiably, that the difference in religion dooth deſire examination and conference. The ſame lawe abhorreth ciuill warres, and dooth lament and deteſt the effuſion of mans bloud: it deſireth alſo the good and quiet of her neighbor, following the ancient prouerb, which ſaith, that man is God to man.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, the law of nature wiſheth generally, a pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable eſtate, to the end that all men ought to liue in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, amitie, equitie, iuſtice, and bleſſednes. Cicero called theſe things,
<note place="margin">Lib. de ſcien.</note> 
                  <hi>Sequi natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ducem,</hi> the following na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as a guide: from whence it proceedeth, that thou, and thy like leagued companions, in writing, councelling, and purſuing the contrary, declare your ſelues to bee enemies to nature, and violaters of the lawe. And as for the other point, touching the example of the Pagans, and their zeale concerning their religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I dare ſay, that if thou with pride of heart, haddeſt vndertooke to reaſon in the behalfe of Satan, to the ende to commend all the wicked religious, which hee hath brought into the worlde, thou couldeſt not haue better proceeded to haue pleaſed him; then in exhorting euerie Countrie to follow the religion which it hath found in the world, without anie other knowing of the cauſe. Tell me, where haſt thou learned this faſhion of arguing? It commeth not from the Apoſtles, who in ſtead of commending the Ethnike religions by ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, did combat with and beate them downe by the authoritie of the word of God.
<note place="margin">Ier. 2.</note> True it is, that in Ieremie, God reaſoning, ſaith, that his people are leſſe conſtant in his truth, than the idolaters are in their errours. But the Prophet did not endeuor, to the end to commend the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, nor the obſtinacie of the idolaters, to the which in the meane time thou doeſt intend. Thou takeſt then this faſhion of arguing from the oracle of Apollo, the which wicked creature did counſell the pagans in times paſt, alwayes to reteine the religions receiued into theyr
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8747:22"/>countrie from all antiquity, without chaunging any thing.
<note place="margin">Xenoph in his Com. Cicero d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus lib. 2.</note> Knoweſt thou not, that amongſt the Pagans ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are not concluded? and much leſſe amongſt Diuines, which do argue altogether by the worde of God. Finally, doeſt thou not knowe that the Gentiles did forſake theyr falſe religions, by the preaching of the Goſpell. Thou haſt done very fairely then in alleadging the Perſians, Greeks, and Romanes in their paganiſme, to the ende that by their example a man ſhould not inquire after the certaintie and aſſurance of the true religion.
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> On our ſide wee ſee agayne the diſciples of Chriſt, with the contentes of his will writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten within his booke, which is the worde of God, &amp; which doth alwayes remaine. But the religions of the Pagans,
<note place="margin">Iſay 40.</note> are periſhed with theyr authors, where it appeareth that thou ſheweſt thy religion to bee more wicked than the Pagans did theirs, for they neither would nor durſt ſerue ſo much wickednes and crueltie, as thou doeſt ſerue thy ſelfe with, in that which thou calleſt the Romiſh Catholicke religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let vs ſee now whether thou canſt profit thy ſelfe any better in thy fourth Article or not. But it will ſooner bee found out, that through a hotte diſeaſe thou wilt fall from the water into the fire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>The fourth Article.</head>
               <p>THe ſumme of this may be drawn to this poynt: that the Catholicks which do mayntaine the kings parte doe breake the ſtatutes and fund mentall lawe of Fraunce. For the proofe of which rupture, this Doctor like vnto a mouſe, that hath but one wretched hoale, neyther knoweth how, nor can alleadge any other text, or reaſon, but a violent and bloudy ſtatute, (or rather the default of a ſtatute) which the laſt Duke of Guize did wreſte by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint againſt the laſt king, imitating beggers, which doe begge almes with a two handed ſworde. My leaguerer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8747:23"/>then, the better to fill his paper, layeth foorth vnto vs here at large the vnderſtanding of his pretended ſtatute, which hee calleth the fundamentall lawe of the Realme, and the ſtatute of vnyon ſolempnly ſworne vnto by all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Towne of Bloys, in the yeare of our Lorde God, 1588. contayning theſe poyntes: (that is to ſaye) that the king woulde holde (ſayth hee) for an inuiolable lawe: Firſt, that hee would lyue and dye in his Catholike Romiſh Religion: Secondly, that hee woulde imploye himſelfe in good earneſt by all the meanes that hee could, to race our the heretikes: Thirdly, that all his ſubiectes ſhoulde ſweare, and binde themſelues vnto the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. And comming to the fourth, that the king dying without children, no heretike ſhould be receyued to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther king or prince.</p>
               <p>Beholde nowe the ſubſtance of the Article. And firſt of all for aunſwere: It is demaunded, who threwe the laſt king downe headlong into his laſt troubles? The houſe of the Guize. Who cauſed him ſhamefully, and in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his lyfe, to come out of Paris? The houſe of Guyze. Who did afterwardes chaſe him from his other Towne of Chartres? The Guyze. Who ſeized himſelfe of the moſt part of his Townes? The houſe of Lorrayne. Who mooued the Frenchmen to treaſon, rebellion, and reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting agaynſt the ſame king? The ſame houſe. Finally, who conſtrayned the poore paſſengers to giue that by by force (which they durſt not refuſe,) to Robbers, which tooke them within Bloys? Euen hee himſelfe, beeing guiltie of high treaſon, a traiterous and wicked vſurper of the eſtate of the Lord.</p>
               <p>This was in the ſame time and ſtate, when the laſt Duke of Guyze demaunded of the laſt king, ſuche an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and deteſtable raunſome. The which this leagued Moonke calleth the Parliament and Statutes of Bloys, and the fundamentall lawe of the Realme. Patience I pray
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8747:23"/>you. Is there any thing more impudent, more falſely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and more ridiculous, than to call this rauening, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion, and conſtraynte; A Statute, and a ſolemne and a fundamentall Lawe of a Realme? Doeſt thou not know, that in the making of a Lawe, the free will of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer is requiſite: And for want whereof the ordinaunce which ſhall bee made agaynſt his will, ſhall bee rather accounted rebellion and felonye, than any iuſt and true Lawe.</p>
               <p>If thou doeſt heere obiecte, that the ſwearing of the King paſſed betweene in ſuche a Statute, thou ſhalt bee aunſwered in lyke ſorte. That is to ſaye, that the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wherein GOD is taken to witneſſe in things,
<note place="margin">Deut. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which in theyr owne nature ought to bee holye and iuſt, requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth likewiſe a free will, that it maye bee thereby able, wholeſomely to foreſee, that it promiſeth nothing vnto God, but that which the conſcience telleth vs, muſt bee iuſtly promiſed and perfourmed. For want whereof, the ſwearing is not onely a nullitie, but alſo ought to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, as beeing made contrary to the inſtitution and ordinaunce of God.</p>
               <p>Whereupon it enſueth, that hee which hath ſworne raſhly, redoubleth his faulte, if hee continueth and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame wicked ſwearing. Then wilt thou replye, that the King in ſuche a caſe ought not to ſweare at all: wherein I agree with thee: but ſo, that thou oughteſt to conſider, that I deteſt and reprooue it, in ſo much as the feare thereof dooth bring manie kinges to this paſſe, for to ſweare rather politikely in Greece, than religiouſly in Iuda, when matters doe concerne theyr eſtates: and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if they fall into anie apparaunt daunger of theyr liues.</p>
               <p>But in ſuch lamentable default, why doeſt thou rather take an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the laſt king, who was conſtrained through the feare of death, than the Guyze, who without
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8747:24"/>any occaſion, did firſt ſhewe himſelfe to bee periured to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the king by his treaſon and rebellion. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeſt thou ſo narrowly ſearch this faulte amongſt kinges and Princes, rather than amongſt Popes, which cal themſelues the vicars of Chriſt Ieſus: which doe but ſport or ieaſt at ſuch oathes, as this worthie ſaying doth teſtifie: <hi>Heretico non eſt ſeruanda fides.</hi> By and by hee will preſent a newe occaſion to ſpeake of an oath, wherefore then, wee ſaye for concluſion of the Article: that euen as money beeing taken away by force by robbers &amp; theeues, cannot bee called a gifte, a preſent, or an almes, giuen or receiued, much leſſe ſuch rapine ought to bee called a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and for leſſe cauſe a fundamentall law of the realme. Vnder the colour of which ſpeech thou doeſt heere ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the truth, which bindeth al the gentlemen of France to this duetie, which is here ſpoken of: foraſmuch as they haue receyued theyr noble poſſeſſions of the firſt kinges, beeing founders of this Crowne, to the intent, and vppon this condition, that they ſhould maintayne the kingdome in the ſtate of the Monarchie, and in the line of the bloud royall, and for the want of ſuch obedience, they ſhould be accounted rebels and felons.</p>
               <p>This is therefore the true fundamentall lawe, iuſt, and approued of all eſtates, &amp; not thy laſt falſe pretended ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, which ſome varlet hath wreſted by ſubtletie, treaſon, and violence, from the handes of his Maiſter. Euen as the laſt king, beeing ſette at libertie, did reuoke it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently after the death of him that had committed ſuche violence agaynſt him, thereby to ſhewe, that ſuch a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked accident, neyther could nor ought to preiudice the trueth, nor the right vſage of any thing. And thus lette vs paſſe further.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:8747:24"/>
               <head>The fifth Article.</head>
               <p>THe fifth Article containeth two points. The firſt is, that the Catholieks which doe helpe the king, doe burie in the duſt, the honour and glorie of Fraunce, which hath receiued this priuiledge aboue al other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of Chriſtendome, that from the time of the firſt chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian king, vnto the laſt king that is now dead, it hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer receiued anie as king, that hath bin anie kinde of waie ſpotted with hereſie. Heerevpon this malecontent doeth knocke and torment himſelfe more than euer hee did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, falling from phrenſie into a rage. For he commeth to this point, that he calleth the king the firſt borne of ſatan. Afterwards he ſaith, that the myracle of healing the goule granted onely to the kings of France, ſhall be loſt in a king being an heretike. Now to the firſt. We anſwere thus, that the honour and glorie of a realme,
<note place="margin">Iohn. 17</note> conſiſteth in the true knowledge of the true God, and in the celebration and right vſage of his pure ſeruice, contained &amp; declared in his word: the kingdomes and countries, hauing kings, which doe acknowledge and practiſe theſe two Articles, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared honorable before God. Whereupon it followeth, that in buſines of religion, the glorie and intereſt of this realme, is nothing at all diminiſhed or hindered, becauſe of the king, ſeeing that he is ſuch a one, and therfore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, he is to be accounted faithfull, and the ſonne of the Church of God. But to the end, that thou ſhalt not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect that I reaſon abſurdly, I will come to thy intention. Thou wouldeſt ſummarily infer and ſay, that in affaires of religion, the glorie of a kingdom lieth in this point, in that that it hath alwaies had kings, which haue acknowledged the Biſhop of Rome decked with all theſe qualities: firſt, to be Gods lieuetenant, the vicar of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> ſucceſſor of the Apoſtles, vniuerſall Biſhop &amp; chiefe &amp; ſoueraigne paſtor of the Church, hauing alſo this authoritie, to change, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and diminiſh, yea, euen to the condemning and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8747:25"/>whome he pleaſeth. Thou calleſt this the honor and glorie of a kingdome. But it hath bin elſe where anſwered and proued vnto thee, that ſuch a doctrine and beleefe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined by the word of God (being the onely touch ſtone) will be found to be ignominious and diſhonorable, ſo farre off is it from all honor and glorie. And as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that which remaineth, wee ought to obſerue the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the times, in the which the kings of France haue beene conuerted to the Chriſtian religion, from the yeere of our Lord God, 472. vntill this time, which was about the ſpace of 1118. yeeres, within which diuers ages many Biſhoppes of Rome being ambitious, ignorant, and ſuperſtitious, haue often times and diuerſly altered &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the pure ſeruice of God. And for my witnes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I take the introduction of this which followeth. The marriage which the Lord inſtituted,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> was heere alreadie forbidden to eccleſiaſticall perſons, as a thing prophane, vnto the which was vrged the vowe of perpetuall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie, and excommunication to them that ſhoulde bee found in falt through ouer-ſight and indiſcretion. The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice as well of Idols as of ſuperſtitious relikes, was recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into vſe, as a thing neceſſarie to ſaluation. Hermita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and dedications of feaſtes and temples, had as much attributed vnto them: in as much as a great portion of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification to ſaluation, was ſought for in them. The ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Croſſe alſo is a parte of it, an abhominable errour to ſaie and beleeue, that in a peece of woode, that may be burned, ſhould conſiſt a peece of the diuine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe. The Prayers and Offerings for the dead, doo ſing the ſame ſong. The adoration of a ſacramentall ſigne brought in ſithence, doeth iuſtifie the ſacrifices of the Pagans, the pride of the Popes, and that of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which doo attribute more vnto themſelues, than euer the ſonne of God did, as hee was in the qualitie of a redeemer.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:8747:25"/>
               <p>All which traditions, idolatries, and ſuperſtitions, are nothing elſe but pure hereſies:
<note place="margin">Serm. 67. ad Eug.</note> for the which cauſe Saint Bernard calleth the bringers in of theſe things, the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Antichriſt, and ſuch Prelates, Pilates. Theſe things will conſtrayne thee to confeſſe, that the greater parte of the kings of France beeing inſtructed in the ſame ſorte, were fedde with a poore foode. Neuertheleſſe I doe agree, that ſuch falſe beleefes cannot bee imputed to he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, but ſimplie to errour, becauſe they did not erre with delight of hart, and much leſſe through mallice, but only thought to doe well. Beſides that, following the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will alleadge the example of two kings of Fraunce, which doe ſhew that thou haſt not ſeene all thinges. The firſt is, of Phillip the fourth, called the fayre, which was not onely accounted and holden as an heretike, but alſo excommunicated of Pope Boniface, the eighth of that name, becauſe hee would not take in hand the voyage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy land, and moreouer, becauſe hee did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that the Pope had right to tranſpoſe kingdomes. The ſecond example concerning Chilperie the ninth king of Fraunce, which helde a damnable opinion touching the article of the Trinitie, and commaunded the Biſhops to preach it. Notwithſtanding all which, Fraunce beeing better taught by the Biſhops that were then, woulde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer enterpriſe to caſt off or forſake neither the one nor the other.</p>
               <p>And now for the ſecond point of the Article, which concerneth the healing of the Goule, a notable myracle (ſayeſt thou) which will haue no force in a king beeing an heretike. To the which ptetended myracle I will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere theſe thinges. Thoſe which returned awaie with theyr Goules incurable, with conditions to ſerue and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh them all theyr life time, doe ſhew, that thou takeſt the coles of Saint Laurence, in the ſtead of the Angell Gabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els feather or quill.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:8747:26"/>
               <p>Secondly, that of the phiſitions which healed them, which were curable, ſhould retourne, they ſhoulde proue, that theyr naturall remedies were of more force than the word and touching. Thirdly, thou canſt not proue, neither by text, nor by example, that the myracles haue bene here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditarie, or tied to one houſe onely. Fourthly, it is an abſurd thing, to infer, that God in giuing ſome miracles to a king dome, hath diſtributed but one kinde. Fiftly, wee ſaie, that God hath neuer giuen or graunted theſe miracles, but for ſome great myſteries, which come not in the vſe of one onely and ſimple healing of corporall diſeaſes, as ſuch as that is of the Goule. If notwithſtanding thou doeſt reply, that ſome haue been healed, ſo as thou doeſt ſuppoſe I wil anſwere, that it ſhould be in like ſort, as if one amongeſt a thouſand of them which go to Saint Claudius, or other ſuch like places ſhould he healed. Thou in the meane time becauſe thou wouldeſt not bee charged with a lie by thy neighbours, doeſt runne into Spaine, to ſearch our witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſaying that there hath beene founde in one onely Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke moe than thirtie thouſand men, which haue bin miraculouſly healed of the Goule. Thou knoweſt that a man dare not tell them that come from farre, that they lie, for which cauſe maiſter Paul Venetus returning from the Iſles of the Eaſt, durſt ſaie, that he found a bird of ſuch an exceſſiue bignes and power, that ſhe tooke vp and carried an Elephant in the aire. Behold heere a great bird, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Spaniards healed of the Goule. Thou ſhouldeſt do bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to praie God for proſperitie of thy king,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> to the end that he may heale the realme of maladies, which are of greate importance, ſuch as are Atheiſme, Epicuriſme, Wars, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions, Cruelties, Iniuſtice, and other iniquities, which range vp and downe in Fraunce, by the miniſtrie of the league, to the deſolation of the mother, and ruine of the childen. And thus let vs paſſe to the Article following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8747:26"/>
               <head>The ſixt Article.</head>
               <p>THis is the ſixt Article, wherin this leaguerly monke ſaith, that the Catholikes of whom he ſpeaketh, do declare themſelues fautors of heretikes, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Catholik Romane religion: from whence he taketh occaſion to compare the hereſie to the adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which doth not torment it ſelfe but with the yron. Then he ſayth, that all thoſe of that religion ought to bee extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and raced out, by the ſame inſtrument. Hee ſayth alſo, that there is no obligation towards the Prince which holdeth, when hee ſetteth himſelfe againſt the ſeruice of God, who commandeth to put all thoſe to death, which do turne awaie the people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true religion, the which he proueth by two texts of Moſes, and in the end hee char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the nobles with auarice, becauſe (ſaith he) they folow the king, to the end to haue ſome recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; therupon he concludeth, that they do leeſe their ſouls. Theſe be the whol contents of the ſixt article. The anſwere to the ſame, The noble men of France, being called by the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallawe of the realme, to the handfaſt keeping of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie of France, as hath bin before ſayd, they are and do feele themſelues bound to the performance of ſuch a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and for want whereof, they ſhew themſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſuch honors and priuiledges, and as for the purpoſe of religion, thou oughteſt to knowe, that they are not orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to eccleſiaſticall charges and functions, to reſolue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. It is inough for them to ſend ſuch diſputations to a louing conference of diuines, folowing the promiſe of the king. This being here admitted to bee neceſſarie, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to equitie, what haſt thou to do to bay or barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gentlemen, exerciſing their duetie? Whileſt that thou doeſt inforce thy ſelfe lyke a member of Satan to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them. The reſt is proued vnto thee, that not to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit idolatry is no hereſie, nor to acknowledge the Biſhop
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8747:27"/>of Rome for ſuch a one as thou doeſt. That maketh thee ſay, that the hereſie ought to be roted out by fire &amp; ſword that is to ſaie, that your Saint Bartolwes daie muſt needes be celebrated from daie to daie in ſtead of amiable confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences: euen ſo as the Iewes did, when they cried, crucify, crucify: by ſuch procedings, worthy ſuch as ye are, ye ſhew your ſelues as honourable and commendable as your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; but the children of God doe abhorre theſe thinges. Foraſmuch as it is written, that murderers ſhal not inherit the kingdome of heauen.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> Chriſt taketh occaſion to proue, that the Iewes which would kill, were the children of the deuill.
<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> And now to the two pointes, which thou wouldeſt haue to ſerue for their wickedneſſe. The firſt is in the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter of Deutronomie,
<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> where it is ſayd, that the falſe Prophets and others, which ſhoulde cauſe the people to turne from their ſeruice of God, or that ſhoulde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues be turned awaie from the true religion for to ſerue ſtrange Gods, ought to be put to death. Heere a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath beene anſwered vnto ſuch a like text, for the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall regard of which, we doe heere adde, that Moſes doth meane by his ſpeech, the ſubiects, and not the kings being ſoueraigne magiſtrates. Secondly, of a defection &amp; reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from God and his religion. Finally, ſuch rigorous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in this deede, ought not to haue bene done but in Iſrael, for the reaſons deſcribed in the firſt Article. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth then, thou doſt falſefie this text, as alſo that which followeth out of Exodus,
<note place="margin">Exo. 32.</note> the two and thirtith Chapter, where it is ſaid, that Aaron hauing forged the golden calf, builded an altar, before the which the people did commit idolatrie, for the which Idolatrie, the Lord tooke ſuch ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous vegeaunce, that he ſlew three thouſand men, thou deceiueſt thy ſelfe in writing of thirtie thouſand. This is a meruailous thing, that the vehemencie and violent affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards the hurting of his king, ſhoulde ſo blind this leaged monke, therby to cauſe him to take the aduerſaries
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8747:27"/>part, euen to the iuſtifying and maintaining of his cauſe. Behold how he doth it. If there bee anie thing in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of religion which the king doth abhorre, they are theſe idolatries. As contrariwiſe, this which maintaineth the fatkitchin of this ſlanderous deceuer, is no other thing but the abuſe which he imputeth to another, imitating the wolfe who troubled the water himſelfe, and yet imputed it to the ſheepe. Doeſt thou not ſee, that thou giueſt thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies thy weapons to beate thy ſelfe with? Thou haſt found out the idolatrie verie wel, but this is not worthy of my anſwere. As alſo the reproching of the Gentlemen for following the king, to the ende to gette ſome great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes. Theſe valiant hearts will anſwere thee, that they haue not their ſoules infected as thine is, conſidering that they follow and accompanie their king,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3. Rom 13.</note> according to the commandement of God, and not in the qualitie or maner of mercenaries, but as noble Lords, who reſpect their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and the charge impoſed vpon them, and in doing this the Lord will bleſſe their labours with a double bleſſing, and inſtead of looſing their ſouls (as thou ſaieſt) they ſhall ſaue them, ſeeing that it is written of thoſe which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes of iuſtice,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12</note> that they ſhal ſhine as the ſtars in the firmament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>The eight Article.</head>
               <p>NOw let vs come to the eighth Article (there hath bin anſwere alreadie made to the ſeuenth) to that which the monkiſh Leaguer ſaith heere, that the Catholikes which doe helpe the king, doe make a double ſchiſme, the one in regard of the Pope, the other in regard of the generalitie of the realme. And for the qualifieng of the firſt, he turneth himſelfe to call the Pope (as aforeſaid) the chiefe vniuerſall &amp; ſoueraigne paſtor of the church: to the which (ſaith he, that obedience is commanded vppon paine of death, Deuteronomie the ſeuenteeth Chapter.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8747:28"/>Now the anſwere to this is, as hath bene before ſaide, that all Chriſtian Catholikes are bound to maintain their kings and Countrie. And alſo that belongeth to Princes of the earth to beare rule and authoritie, and not to Biſhops, and as for the point of religion, hee of Rome hath nothing to doe, no not halfe a league out of his dioceſſe, ſo farre off is he from hauing anie thing to do ouer all France.
<note place="margin">Deu. 17 Num. 16</note> Wherev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it foloweth, that the example of Corath, Dathan, and Abirom, with the text of Deutronomie which thou alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, make nothing to the matter. Firſt beeing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the charge of a ſoueraigne high Prieſt, whereof Moſes ſpeaketh,
<note place="margin">Heb. 8</note> was giuen by diuine inſtitution, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly vnto the Iewes, figuring theyr Meſſias, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the which was ended at his death. This is then an errour, yea hereſie it ſelfe, to call a Biſhoppe at this daie by that name, and to conſtitute him in the ſame degree. The which ſhoulde bee to bring Chriſte backe againe from heauen,
<note place="margin">Rom 10</note> as if hee had not ended the figures of the lawe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the example of Corath, touching the other ſchiſme, doth playnly ſhew forth thoſe which doe reuolt from theyr ſoueraigne magiſtrates, and thoſe alſo which will not acknowledge them as Magiſtrates, ſuch a one was Corath and his accomplices,
<note place="margin">Num. 16</note> when as they woulde not acknowledge Moſes anie more to bee theyr head.</p>
               <p>Seeing therefore, that thou and thy companions do the like vnto your king, it followeth, that ye are culpable of the ſchiſme, which falſely yee impoſe vppon others. In dooing thus, you imitate Achab, when as hee asked the Prophet Eliah,
<note place="margin">1. Kin. 17.18</note> ſaying, Art not thou hee which trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt all Iſrael? Vppon the which like occurrence, wee may alſo aunſwere with the Prophet, That it is thou thy ſelfe, and the houſe of thy Romiſh Father. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth thhrefore agayne and alwayes wyll, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8747:28"/>thou doeſt falſefie theſe textes and examples, in applying them for an ambitious wretch, which hath nothing at all to doe in Fraunce. Thou haſt then fairely tormented thy ſelfe in calling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rebels &amp; heretiks, which will not admit of the primacie of Rome, for an Article of the faith. France hath the iuriſdiction, aſwell of eccleſiaſticall as politike matters in it ſelfe, and wherewith the inhabitants of Rome haue nothing to doe. Alſo know this, that there are in this realme as learned Biſhoppes, iuſt, and wiſe, as there bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in Italie. Finally, it hath beene prooued, that thy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh preheminence is altogether contrary to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the ſonne of God,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. Luk. 22.</note> which hath expreſſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſuch dominations to Biſhops, when he ſayth; that the kinges of the nations beare rule ouer them, but it ſhall not be ſo with you. Thou att afraide that the aboliſhing of ſome eccleſiaſticall abuſe ſhoulde doe ſome wrong vnto thy belly: but ieaſt not at it. Caſt thy ſelfe and thyne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires vppon the Lorde, and ſo thou ſhalt haue reſt in thy ſoule. And as for the reſt of thy infectious ſmokie ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which thou doeſt continually blaſt out of thy mouth againſt thy king, I leaue them vnto the diſpoſition of the windes. And yet in the meane time remember with thy ſelfe what iudgements the Lord threw vpon the heade of Semei, for the like offence.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>The ninth Article.</head>
               <p>IT followeth in this ninth article, to ſhew how this Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate Monke doth accuſe the Catholickes with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie, which will not reuolt nor carry Spaniſh heartes, but for proofe wherof, he neyther knoweth how, nor can alleadge any other text, but the forenamed pretended ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, contained in the fourth Article, wreſted as before. Thou doeſt heere inuite mee to theſe repetitions, yet aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere mee once againe I pray thee.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:8747:29"/>
               <p>Letting that paſſe, ſeeing that the beſt and greateſt part aſwell of the Nobles, as of the thirde eſtate of Fraunce, haue neyther promiſed nor ſworne, as thou wouldeſt make them beleeue: wherefore wee ought to obſerue that which followeth.</p>
               <p>If a man be bound by an oath to ſome iuſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary duety towardes his countrey, hee ought not to falſefie it by any preiudiciall promiſe, which ſhall bee contrarie to the ſame being firſt made. Now let vs applye this thing. The Gentlemen of Fraunce, by the aboueſaide fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lawe, haue plighted their faith and homage vnto their king, in promiſing to defend him, together with the eſtate of his kingdome: whereupon it followeth, that neyther at the inſtigation of the Guize, the Spaniards, nor the Popes, they ought to breake theyr firſt oath.
<note place="margin">Math. 21.</note> Thou ſayeſt, that Religion, beeing of greateſt importaunce, dooth abſolue them in ſuch a caſe. But thou mayeſt bee aunſwered, beyond that which hath already been ſpoken, that it doth rather ratifie and confirme ſuche dueties, than other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>And as for the great importaunce thereof, the which is ſpoken for other reſpectes, touching the ſeruice of God, beeing ſpirituall and heauenly, which dooth nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh the priuiledges and rightes of the gouernours of the worlde. Where doeſt thou finde, that Guyze, or that a Biſhoppe of Rome haue any right or reaſon to diſpence with the ſubiectes for breaking theyr oathes which they haue made vnto theyr kinges? The Pagan Prieſtes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer produced ſuche a deteſtable and horrible Maxiome. Remember thy ſelfe of the oath whiche Herode made,
<note place="margin">Mat. 14.</note> which coſt the Church the death of Iohn Baptiſt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I demaund of thee: was this tyraunt bounde to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte his promiſe: yes as much as if hee had beene bound to haue made two deuils of one: And if a man bee bounde to kill his children, hauing promiſed and ſworne it to God.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8747:29"/>Doeſt thou not knowe,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 45.</note> that it is neuer lawfull to ſweare to doe euill? Let vs nowe applye this phyſically. Thou and thy lyke haue induced ſome Frenchmen beeing euill aduiſed, and worſe infourmed, to the ſupporting of the Spanyard, and Lorrayne, towardes the thruſting out of the King, and for the bringing in of an inquiſition, and a ſtraunge gouernement. From thence is it come to paſſe, that many of the Gentlemens conſciences of Fraunce, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowne and conſidered the iniquitie of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, are readuiſed, and repentant, for being wrapped within the aboue named condemnation of Chore,
<note place="margin">Num. 16</note> who will denye, that they haue not had iuſt occaſion to doe this?</p>
               <p>But becauſe thou loueſt bloud, thou wouldeſt induce it to the example of Herode: to the ende, that they maye bring thee a thouſand heades, to dedicate them vnto the ſame ſacrifices, as Buſiris did, when hee ſacrificed his hoſtes to Iupiter. Take heede that thou art not taken as the Dragons are,
<note place="margin">Plin lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 12.</note> which ſucke vp ſo much bloud from the Elephant, that they make themſelues drunke, and ſo they dye.</p>
               <p>This is nowe aunſwered and ſayde vppon the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallitie of thy queſtion. And nowe I come to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular poynte: where thou doeſt alleadge two quotinges of Scripture, for the vpholding and maintenaunce of thy lewd and wicked ſwearing: the one out of the nineteenth Chapiter of Leuiticus:
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19. Deut. 23.</note> and the other out of the three and twentith of Deuteronomie. In the firſt it is ſayde, You ſhall not ſweare by my name in telling of lyes. And in the ſecond it is ſayde; Thou ſhalt performe thy vowes, which thou haſt vowed vnto the Lorde thy God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I aunſwere: that in ſuch preceptes, and other ſuche lyke, alwayes two thinges are to bee vnderſtoode and forbidden. The firſt is, that there bee no euill kinde of ſwearing, ſuche as is when any one bindeth himſelfe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8747:30"/>to vndertake &amp; execute ſome wicked things. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that wee ought alwayes to rule and ſquare our oathes to the will of God ſpecified in his worde: for if one offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him the price of a dogge,
<note place="margin">Deut 23.</note> it will be vnto him abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, much more then the bloud of mankind, the which notwithſtanding this Monke of the league deſireth aboue all thinges.</p>
               <p>This beeing heere admitted, the third text which thou alledgeſt out of the fift chapter of Zacharie, maketh clean againſt thy ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Zacha. 5.</note> ſeeing that it is a falſe kinde of ſwearing by the name of God, when one ſweareth otherwiſe than he hath commaunded: and alſo, when one ſweareth to do euill. Thoſe which ſo prophane the name of God, ought to feare the curſe and iudgement which thou talkeſt of: but thoſe which do obey him, need nothing at all to feare. Thy propoſition then is found altogether to bee falſe and wicked. And to this ende, praiſing and approuing the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, which the Iacobine frier thy brother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted: thou ſayſt thus of the laſt king; that God hath confounded him, as if God &amp; the deuill had conſpired together ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable facte. Doeſt thou not drawe vpon thy ſelfe the vengeaunce of God in iuſtifiyng of ſuch wicked crimes? The weapons of iniquitie are in your habitations (ſayth Iacob,
<note place="margin">Gen 49.</note>) Curſed be your wrath and furie, for it is impudent, and wicked. Thou wouldeſt bee ignoraunt of this, that the murderers ſhall not inherite the kingdome of God.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> Canſt thou better iuſtifie the moſte horrible maſſacre of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans? Thou wilt alleadge heere the example of Pope Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus thy ſoueraigne, which hath approued the ſame iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by an expreſſe booke: and thus much for this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>The tenth Article.</head>
               <p>THe malcontent ſaith in this Article, that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes which accompany the king, do fall into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall infamie, and cauſe the kingdome likewiſe to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8747:30"/>be accounted infamous, as two or three of his Canons d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> import, being framed to his minde. This obiection I ſaye, hath beene aunſwered in the fift Article, and heere onely will we adde, that the infamie of a kingdome conſiſteth in the abuſe of Religion, ignorance, Atheiſme, Epicuriſme, ſchiſmes, rebellions, barbarous actions, cruelties, and lewd riotouſnes: in the trade of which iniquities, the children of the league are moſt skilfull, yea euen without compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of any others. As the proceedinges in receiuing the Spanyardes into Fraunce doe witneſſe, to whoſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit theſe traitors of all men moſt wretched and infamous, do ſell theyr libertie, and the libertie of their kinſfolkes, wiues and children, without taking any pledge of them, for the ſame. Can ther be a more infamous thing thoght of then this, as ſo to yeeld themſelues as ſlaues with reioicing of heart to the Spanyards? To the end, to be one day hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him, not onely after the manner as Pharao in olde time vſed the Iſraelites in Egypt. But in like manner as hee himſelf handleth &amp; vſeth the Mores, aſwel thoſe of Africa, as of India. And thus maye the infamous of the kingdome be eaſily diſcerned, which are not thoſe which woulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and deliuer it from ſuch hardſhippe and ſlauiſh ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de. Alas it is knowne wel enough that men naturally do loue their owne libertie, from whence proceeded this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient prouerbe, which ſayth, that libertie is better than all the golde in the worlde. Neuertheles, theſe madde people enemies to themſelues, would be ridde of it, as of a thinge of ſmall value or price. Wherefore this doth verefie, that if there be any infamous wretch in the worlde, that thou art he, which by thy vnnaturall precepts doſt cauſe the holye Chriſtian religon (ſo farre forth as in thee lyeth) to be had in execration, and holden in contempt of all barbarous people, which can but reade thy prophane writinges, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding altogether to the deſolation and ruine of thine owne countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:8747:31"/>
               <head>The eleuenth Article.</head>
               <p>LEt vs paſſe the reſte of the Articles, and come vnto the eleuenth, which importeth, that the aforeſayde Catholickes doe betraye theyr Mother Church, in ſuche ſorte as Iudas did his maiſter Chriſt, or as Sonnes that will not ſuccour theyr mother, when as one woulde ſtrangle or choake her: And afterwards comming to the application, this Criminall Iudge calleth the king, the capitall enemie of the Church, and the Catholickes which followe him, his hang-men, denyers of Chriſtianitie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyons of Nembroth, and more barbarous and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall than the Scithians.</p>
               <p>To beginne mine aunſwere with, I woulde haue thee firſt aſſure thy ſelfe that thou wilt bee garniſhed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte of proofes, as much as euer any man was, that hath made a trade of dawbing paper. Verefie thy propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by good textes and argumentes, and if it commeth to paſſe that thou haſt any reaſon, it ſhall bee graunted: but if contrarywiſe, then the lawe is agaynſt thy ſelfe. And if beeing not willing to proceede anye further, then holde thy peace, for thou declareſt thy ſelfe to bee vnworthie of anye writing or aunſwere.</p>
               <p>For the which purpoſe, ſirſt I heere aunſwere thee, that the diuerſe charges and different callinges ought to bee diſtinguiſhed, to the ende, that the Shoomaker maye not meddie with the Taylor, nor the Blacke-ſmith with the Locke-ſmith. Nowe if the Mechanicall artes doe require ſuch an obſeruation, much more then thoſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall ſciences, and a great deale more thoſe ſciences and diuerſities of eſtates, which concerne the generall and publike adminiſtrations of the worlde. Euen as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of Ioathan doth teach vs,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> ſaying; that the Olyue tree dooth contente her ſelfe with her fatneſſe, and the figge
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8747:31"/>tree with her ſweetneſſe, without that, that either of them dooth trouble each others tree. Signifiyng thereby, that euerie one ought to contente himſelfe, and to follow his vocation, vnto the which the Lorde hath called him, without buſying himſelfe in anye other mens, for feare leaſt ſome greeuons puniſhment ſhoulde fall vpon him according to the example of Ozias king of Iuda,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 20.</note> who was ſtriken with leproſie, when as hee woulde haue vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the office of the high Prieſt, which did altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belonge and appertayne vnto the children of Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</p>
               <p>Euen ſo then the Biſhoppe ought to contente hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with his Eccleſiaſticall adminiſtration, and the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman onely with the handling of his ſworde. So then, when euerie tree ſhall contente it ſelfe with the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his owne fruite, ſhall all thinges goe well. This beeing heere graunted, as neceſſary, rightfull, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable: what will this Leaguerer ſaye, when as hee tormenteth hymſelfe ſo diuerſlye agaynſt the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which doe not take vppon them at his will and pleaſure, the affayres of the Romiſh Religion, for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende it without anye further knowledge, the paſſions of his prelates, to the vtter ruine and ouerthrowe of theyr king, of themſelues, and of theyr countrey? The which they haue taken vppon them to defende, leauing the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations of Religion vnto Diuines. And thus much for the firſt aunſwere.</p>
               <p>And nowe to the ſeconde: where I hope to contente the Reader with reaſons of ſome force, taken from the holie Scriptures, and not from lyes and falſe ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according to thy faſhion. And that wee maye the better doe this, lette vs knowe what this worde Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church dooth meane, and what are the markes, and who are the true members of the ſame. This knowledge is heere moſt neceſſarie, foraſmuch as in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8747:32"/>ſteade of the Chriſtian Church inſtituted by Ieſus Chriſt, this Leaguerer dooth alwayes propoſe vnto vs a Romiſh Church, containing the idolatries and ſuperſtitions of the Biſhop of the ſame. In thy opinion, if Rome ſhould be loſt, what would become of all Chriſtendome? Leauing then this abhominable errour, to thinke anye further that the vniuerſall Church hangeth on the Romane, we wil ſpeake of the thing that followeth the deſcription which the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture maketh,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Rom. 8. Iohn. 6. 1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 5</note> calling the Chriſtian Church an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Saints, being called according to the ordinance of God in Ieſus Chriſt, and gathered from all the nations of the worlde, by the preaching of the Goſpell, to the ende, that they maye obtaine life euerlaſting. Alſo the Apoſtles haue ſpoken in the ſame ſorte of the Chriſtian Church. They haue called it the houſe of God, the body of Chriſt, &amp; the edification of the ſame body. For the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and entertainement of the which, Saynt Paule ſayth, that God hath giuen fiue ſortes of men,
<note place="margin">Eph 4.</note> which are the Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, Doctors, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</p>
               <p>The ſame Apoſtles doe alwayes witneſſe, that Ieſus Chriſt hath receyued this honour of his Father, to bee the onely head and ſoueraigne Paſtor of his Church. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1.</note> hearken what Saint Paule ſayth: God (ſaith he) hath ſet Ieſus Chriſt at his right hande, in the heauenly places, and hath ſubiected all things vnder him, that he might be the heade of the Church: where wee ought to note this, that the Apoſtle wrote this after that Ieſus Chriſt was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heauen. To the ende, that the Pope which hath inueſted himſelfe into the Empyre of this diuine ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> might not ſaye, that after his aſcenſion, the Church ſhoulde neede an other heade. The which if it had beene a thing that were neceſſary, the Apoſtle woulde neuer haue omitted and let paſſe ſuch an Article of ſo great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:8747:32"/>
               <p>This is then a monſtrous thing,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> to giue to the Church two heads and ſoueraigne paſtors. It is to bee ſeene alſo then, that concerning the gouernment and conduction of the ſame, the holy Scripture maketh no mention of the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Rome, when as otherwiſe it nameth it a reuolt and an Apoſtate:
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2</note> thereby to deſcribe and make it ſeeme odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to all good and well diſpoſed people. To be briefe, the holy Scripture doth repreſent the holy Catholike &amp; chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian church, as one entire bodie, hauing the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of diſperſed throughout the whole world, &amp; of the which bodie Chriſt is the onely head, and the Churches diſpear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heere and there are members of the ſame.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1</note> Seeing then that there is but one Catholike Church, it followeth, that the Church of Rome cannot be it, but onely a parte, as a member of the bodie. Theſe reaſons and authorities, doe maintaine, that the aboueſayd Catholikes are nothing at all traiterous to the Chriſtian Church, when as they defend themſelues, their king, and their Countrie, as well agaynſt the Spaniard, Italian, &amp; Lorraine, as alſo finally againſt the Leaguers of the Countrie, be they eccleſiaſtical or others. Beſides that, the Catholikes which are enimies to the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers will anſwere, that it is ſufficient for them to auouch and acknowledge, for their ſpirituall mother Hieruſalem,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4</note> which is on high, which is free, and called in the holy ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the mother of vs all, they haue nothing then to doe with the terreſtriall, which is below,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 4.</note> and which ingende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her children vnto bondage, declared by Saint Paul, to be enimies to the Church, and not the others. It is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for Chriſtians to be of the Chriſtian church, deſcribed by the Apoſtles, in the which we conſider three principall markes.
<note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The firſt conſiſteth in the doctrine as well of the lawe, as of the Goſpel, being well applied and vnderſtood. The ſecond, in the right vſage ofthe Sacramentes. The third, in the obedience to the doctrine and miniſtrie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when thou canſt not denie, but that by the wicked of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8747:33"/>and tyrannie of the Popes, the eſſentiall markes of all things moſt neceſſarie to Chriſtian religion, are wanting for the moſt parte, as hath beene amplie ſhewed vnto you in the diſcourſe dedicated to the Nobilitie, where hath beene prooued, that yee haue lefte none of the Articles of the faith pure nor intire, and that if there bee anie here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in the worlde, thou and thy companions are they, namely,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> who by your traditions haue buried the benefites of the paſſion, death, reſurrection, and aſcention of Ieſus Chriſt, which God onely hath made vnto vs wiſedome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and redemption. Thus leauing this fountaine, yee ſend your ſchollers to the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian parchments, bulles, and traditions of Rome, and yet notwithſtanding thou giueſt the allarum, and cauſeſt fyre to come forth from the brambles,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> to burne thoſe that will not augment and defend thy cookerie, together with thy tyrannie and Spaniſh inquiſition: and doeſt call the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of ſuch treaſons and cruelties, heretikes and vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers agaynſt the Church, ſayth the pilgrime. But thou oughteſt to knowe, that theſe good people are appointed to defend the veritie and puritie of chriſtianitie, and not the abuſe of the Romiſh Church. This beeing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, applie that which thou doeſt adde vnto thy ſelfe, and to thy fellowes, that is, that this hereſie is the cauſe of all theſe preſent euilles, remembring with thy ſelfe, that for the maſſacres, treaſons and rebellions, vengeaunce doth manifeſt it ſelfe from heauen agaynſt the authours and executers thereof, and not agaynſt thoſe which deſire the reformation of the Church.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> Heere thou doeſt complaine that the vſe of your Churches are diuerted and chaunged. This is great pittie, if it bee thus, that they are not nowe prophaned, as when the praiſes of the creatures were ſung,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> the which yee dyd there worſhippe in the ſteade of the creator: and as when hee preached the Romiſh ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6</note> in ſtead of Chriſt crucified. If one ought ſo to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8747:33"/>himſelfe for the beating downe of the Churches, alaſſe then how many of the faithfull haue yee maſſacred beeing the true temples of God. I perceiue alwayes, that thou feareſt more ſome eccleſiaſticall reformation, than anie other thing cauſeth thee ſo to inſiſt vppon the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Emperours and kings, which after theyr ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, haue induced the people to the chaunge of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But remember thy ſelfe, that in the eight Article I haue counſelled thee to commit thy ſelfe and thine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres vnto the Lorde, and thou ſhalt finde reſte in thy ſoule.</p>
               <p>And as for the ſecond, remember thy ſelfe of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which Gamaliel did giue vnto the chiefe Prieſts of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, ſaying: If thy counſell bee of men, it ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayle, but if it be of God it will not moue.
<note place="margin">Act 5.</note> Now for the third, it will bee proued, that thy maxime is not alwayes true, as the Chriſtians of the primitiue Church doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the faythfull of our time, which doe loue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to die, than to imitate the idolatrie of theyr forrayne Princes.</p>
               <p>Finallie, thou ſaieſt, that the plaintes contayned in this Article, are ſufficicient to draw downe the ſtarres from heauen. In deede you haue done that by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of your perſecutions, when as yee haue ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and cauſed ſo many thouſands of the faythfull to fall, which are compared to the ſtarres in the heauen. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou doeſt falſely impute ſuch ſlanders vppon thoſe which doe defend theyr king and their Countrie,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 6</note> as alſo thou doeſt declare thy ſelfe a traitor to Ieſus Chriſt, when in ſteade of defending the puritie &amp; veritie of his chriſtian Church: thou doeſt defende the abuſes of the Romaine, which is reſiſtance and violence offerep vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:8747:34"/>
               <head>The twelfth Article.</head>
               <p>LOoking into the contents of the twelfth article, wee ſhall finde that this leaguall aduocate ſaith, that the Catholikes to whom he ſpeaketh, doe betray theyr kingdom, and procure the deſolation &amp; ruine of the ſame, for proofe whereof, firſt he ſaith, that about thirtie yeres ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence, this hereſie made ſome woundes which do bleede yet. Secondly, that within theſe fifteene yeeres the king of Nauarre hath ſpoyled the realmes by ſtrangers, and hath vſed verie many barbarous actes of hoſtilitie and cruelties againſt the orders of the ſame. Thirdly, that he is a Nero in maliciouſneſſe and crueltie. Fourthly, from whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that it is verie badly done to giue the ſwoord of S. Paul into his hand, and the key of Saint Peter. And heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon this leaguer tormenteth himſelf, &amp; cryeth, help, help my friends, for theſe Catholikes are traitours vnto the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholike Church, the which they would chaſe out of this Countrie of France, contrarie to the propheſie of Saint Remye, and ſuch like as followeth. And now for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, firſt I deſire thee, that ſeeing thou haſt tooke paines to haue beene deliuered of theſe lying affirmations, to bee patient to heare the denialles which are moſt true, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then at the moſt generall pointes. We anſwere in the firſt place, that the aforeſayd arguments haue beene ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared and verified, that the Catholikes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of thou ſpeakeſt, are not anie kinde of waie traiterous to Chriſtian religion, ſeeing that they are obedient vnto the commandements of the ſame, inaſmuch as they doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſoueraigne magiſtrates. Which it approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and commendeth in the behalfe of God their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we haue proued that the chriſtian religion being folowed in the reformation of the ſame, containeth
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8747:34"/>no poynt of hereſie. Thirdly, wee haue produced the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of eſtates, and difference of charges: where it hath beene already ſhewed, that the Noblemen, and all other men of warre ought to ſuffice themſelues with the corſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let and ſworde, leauing the diſputations of religion vnto the eccleſiaſticall aſſemblies. Fourthly, heere muſt bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited againe the fundamentall lawe, which bindeth the Nobilitie to the eſtabliſhing of the French Monarchie within the line of the bloud royall: what looſenes woulde it bee accounted in the Noblemen, if they ſhould not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye themſelues with care againſt the enemies of the kingdome, and aboue all, againſt the Spanyardes, which would at this daye not onely thruſt out, but alſo extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the king for euer if they could? For the which cauſe, I will alleadge a forceable ſaying of a Doctor being a late writer to this purpoſe, ſpeaking thus: And as for this kind of people which do no ſeruice in the worlde, but to ſhedde innocent bloud, couering theyr cruelties with a cloake of religion, I eſteeme them worthie no other aunſwere, but that which is to be giuen to theeues, which ſhould pleade agaynſt thoſe which are impannelled for the country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhoulde not carry the ſworde for their defence. And it maketh mee to remember this execrable Romaine Fimbria (ſayth hee) the which hauing fayled to kill Sceuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, threatned not to delay it, becauſe hee ſhould not be left vnſlaine.</p>
               <p>Conſider and apply this aunſwere, whileſt that I doe viſite the other arguments of thy Article. Thou ſayeſt that within theſe thirty yeares this hereſie hath made ſome wounde that bleedeth yet, vnto the which thou haſt beene already aunſwered, that the abuſes, behauiours, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies of the Guyze haue cauſed this miſchiefe, and not the reformation of the Church. Thou addeſt alſo, that within theſe fifteene yeares laſt paſt, the king hath waſted Fraunce in exerciſing diuerſe and moſte cruell actions of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8747:35"/>hoſtilitie. And to aunſwere the ſame, it hath beene ſayde, that by his meekneſſe, tollerations, ſufferances, weet and gentle be hauiours, his enemies haue obiected the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry againſt him:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> ſaying, that hee vſed ſubtletie, thereby to get the good will both of the one and the other. Read and ſee, and thou ſhalt finde, that it was the Guize that playde the part of Nero, and not the king. But hee is an heretike, ſaieſt thou. To this ſong, hauing beene a thouſand times repeated, thou haſt beene aunſwered a hundred times per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently and ſufficiently: and ſo much for this.</p>
               <p>In the ende thou concludeſt, that it is very ill doone to giue the ſword of Saint Paule, and the keyes of Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, into his hande: that is to ſaye, to conſtitute him king. The which poynt alſo hath beene amply and diuerſly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Articles going before, where hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that no matter or occaſion doth offer it ſelfe, whereby the king ought eyther to be reiected or refuſed, who hath both from God and man, a lawfull calling, to gouerne and conduct the Realme of Fraunce. This Maxime is confeſſed of all men, not being preuented or lead with a fore iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And as for the alluſion which thou makeſt vnto the ſworde of Saint Paule, and the keyes of Saint Peter, thy maiſters haue drawne this prophanation and trumperie, from the falſe interpretation which they haue giuen vnto a text in the two and twentith chapter of Saint Luke, where Ieſus fore-telling the Apoſtles of the perſecutions which they ſhoulde ſuffer after his death,
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> admoniſhed them to make prouiſion offoure thinges, that is to ſaye, of purſes, ſcribbes, coates, and ſwordes: ſignifiyng by ſuche Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors, that they ought to prepare themſelues to ſuffer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges. But they were yet ſo ignoraunt, that in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two ſwordes, they thought themſelues able to reſiſte by the ſame: wherefore Ieſus mocking them, ſayde; It is enough.</p>
               <p>Heere is great matter wherewith to drawe your two
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8747:35"/>offices of Magiſtracie, ſuch mockeries are therfore vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of any aunſwere: as alſo the propheſies which thou calleſt Saint Remyes, the which hath neyther right nor power, to treade downe thoſe of the ſpirite of God, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling that the Cittie with ſeuen mountaines,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 17.</note> which hath had great gouernement and rule ouer the earth, ſhall bee razed out. And as for the examples of the Gothes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enemies of the Church which thou doeſt heere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande, ſuch perſecutors haue no communitie with the Princes, which loue and do procure the aduauncement of the kingdome of Chriſt. Alſo in regard of any other thing touching the kings of Fraunce, it hath beene aunſwered in the firſt Article. And alſo paſſing further, thou doeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt the Noblemen beeing enemies to the league, the deſolation and confuſion of the Realme. But I ſee that thou haſtread Eſops fabules, ſeeing that thou playeſt the parte of a Woolfe, troubling the water before the ſheepe. Who aduaunce ſuch miſchiefes more than yee, by the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous miniſterie of your rebellions and reuolts? Yea ſaieſt thou, but the kinges of Fraunce in theyr ſacring, doe take the ſworde at the hands of the Biſhop, for to beate downe heretikes. And I aunſwere thee agayne, that the king did take it at the hands of God, to do this if need ſhould ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, being not bound to receyue it at the hands of a man of the Church, who hath nothing to do with the materiall ſworde.</p>
               <p>Thou doeſt alſo further aſſume, that the king of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre, dooth promiſe to intertayne two religions into this kingdome: but what reaſon dyd hinder him from recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing foure or eyght? Nowe I maye aunſwere, that in this place thy memorie fayleth thee, for thou haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſayde, that hee woulde aboliſh the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and nowe thou accuſeſt him, that hee would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it. But hee may admit mo ſaieſt thou. The which I anſwere, doth not conclude: for ſuch a ſoueraigne would
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8747:36"/>tollerate a thing, which hee eſteemeth neceſſary for the maintenance of his eſtate, and the which will haue greate reſpect vnto other thinges which ſhoulde bee preiudiciall vnto him. And as for the profeſſion of Atheiſme, whereof thou ſpeakeſt, heere with Saint Barnard and Petrarke, wee exile this Epicure into the Towne of Rome: for it ſhall be lodged and accepted better of there, than elſewhere. Thou makeſt mention alſo of the maſſacres and martirdomes come to paſſe in England, and in Bearne; which if it bee true, then is it paſſiuely, and not actiuely: for thoſe which make profeſſion of the reformed religion, haue not learned Chriſt Ieſus ſo: they leauing ſuche more than barbarous cruelties of murdering the faintes,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> vnto thoſe of whome S. Iohn ſpeaketh in the Apocalyps. And to that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth, I dare very well ſay, that a ſubtletie of thine own put into the vttermoſt cabinet of thy conſcience, cauſeth thee heere to ſpeake ſo figuratiuely, and as one may ſay, by the figure Antiphraſis, ſeeing that thou calleſt the moſte pernitious, wicked &amp; ſeditious men in all Europe, martirs: which had as martirs of Satan vowed to their maiſter, the ruine aſwell of their ſoueraigne prince, as of their country. For what man is there of our time which knoweth anie thing of the affaires thereof, which dooth not knowe verie well, that there hath neuer beene any perſecution ſtyrred vp, either in Bearne, or in England, againſt the Romiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion? And who knoweth not certainly, that thoſe whom thou ſpeakeſt of, were puniſhed only becauſe of their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, rebellions, and coniurations? Alſo who ſeeth not, that thou wouldeſt make of euill good, and good euill? And that thou doſt iuſtifie the wicked, that by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples thou mighteſt produce others like vnto them into Fraunce, and alſo incite and incourage them to the lyke crime? But that which God doth keepe, is well garded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8747:36"/>
               <head>The thirteenth Article.</head>
               <p>NOw onely remaineth the laſt of thy Articles to be ſpoken of, the contentes whereof I maye rightly compare to a towne ditch, or ſinke, into the which is powred all manner of vncleannes and filthines: for thou haſt diſtilled heereinto the quinteſſence or very ſubſtance of thy wicked ſpirits, to maintaine therby (if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) that white is blacke, the good euill, the light darknes, and the truth a lye: as ſhall be better ſeene and proued in the examination of the ſame. Thou haſt inſerted the ſame poynt into the third Article, but heere thou giueſt a more ample expoſition of it. And the ſumme of it is this; that the aforeſaid Catholicks are worſe than the Iewes, Turks, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and Heretikes, yea than beaſtes themſelues. The which pretended Maxime thou doſt defend in three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall heads: and from the beginning of the firſt thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Catholickes which are enemies to the League, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed; becauſe they followe a king which is of an other religion than theirs: yea, and that which thoſe Infidelles would not do, which thou haſt already named. For the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of my anſwere, I muſt be conſtrained once againe to ſay, that thy ſuppoſitions (which are nothing but falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods and lyes) haue beene by thee ſo often ſaid and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that they doe declare thee to be vnworthy of any aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere by writing. It hath beene ſufficiently prooued vnto thee, that the king is not found in any thing to be an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike. Secondly, that the falſe vnderſtanding or beleefe in the caſe of religion, dooth not take awaye the power of rule and gouernement from kinges and princes of the world.</p>
               <p>And in the third place, that not only the Iewes, Pagans, and heretikes, but the Chriſtians are oftentimes ſubmitted and put in ſubiection, to the gouernement of many kings,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8747:37"/>being iefidels and heretikes, the which proofes haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared thee, and now of new againe doe declare thee to be a deceiuer, and a lyar, euen as the ſlaunders doe importe, which thou impoſeſt vpon thoſe of the reformed religion, in ſaying that they neuer woulde, nor will haue anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kings but of their owne religion: the which they haue debated on this thirtie yeeres, as thou ſaieſt. For aunſwere whereunto, I woulde call thy conſcience to witneſſe, if it were not hardened in ſuch ſorte as Saint Iude ſpeaketh of. Wherefore leauing it to glut it ſelfe with ſleepe, I will ſummon thoſe before God, which waken betimes in the morning, to teſtifie before his diuine Maieſtie, whether all theſe effectes and euentes paſſed, haue not verefied, that wee haue alwayes acknowledged, approoued, and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all our kinges which went before vs, as men ſent from God: our often prayers for their proſperitie, and the reſte of our actions, do giue the lye vnto all thoſe which do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe vs of the contrarie.</p>
               <p>But your deteſtable murders,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> and maſſacres, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the children of the ſlaughter houſe of Rome. If thou doeſt obiect vnto vs any of our defences, the houſe of Guize hath vrged and conſtrained vs neceſſarily &amp; iuſtlie thereunto. Thou knoweſt it well enough: but that ought to bee accounted amongſt the enterpriſes which yee haue done, and do againſt the king, and the eſtate of the realme. The ende dooth crowne the worke. Thou haſt nothing to do heere then to call M. Caluin as a witneſſe, reproaching him,
<note place="margin">Dan. 6</note> in that thou ſaieſt he hath written vpon Daniel, that the earthly princes doe depoſe themſelues of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when as they preſume againſt God: yea, that then it is better to ſpitte in their faces than to obey them. Let a man of conſcience reade throughout his whole Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and there he ſhall find thee to be a malitious lyar, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there is no mention made of anie ſuche thinge as thou doeſt obiect. For he ſayth, that Princes ought to bee
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8747:37"/>diſobeyed onely, when as they woulde conſtraine men to offend God. But that hath no communitie with thy reuolt. Thou doeſt replie, that therfore Maiſter Caluin &amp; Maiſter Bezado condemne an heretike to death. We anſwer, that that maketh thee to agree with vs <hi>ſecundum quid:</hi> that is to ſay, by the means that fiue neceſſary concurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do there meet together, which are. Firſt the ordinance of a ſoueraigne Magiſtrate. The ſecond, a certaine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of hereſie. The third, the louing and free conference betweene him which is in errour, and thoſe which do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him. The fourth, a manifeſt hardening, and malitious ſtiffe-neckednes, in continuing in his falſe beleefe. The fifth, where wee doe adde (as aforeſaid) that Princes ought not in this caſe, nor in ſuche lyke, to bee handled with the ſame forme and rigour as theyr ſubiectes are: and that this cenſure ought to bee applyed to the crime. To the purpoſe of which application, (if the libertie of confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence might bee graunted to Diuines) I dare aſſure thee, they would finde ſufficient matter, to obiecte againſt thee that, which was obiected againſt Sophiſtus, who woulde haue proued, that Diogines was neuer any man: to whom it was aunſwered: Conclude that of thy ſelfe, which thou wouldeſt ſaye of an other, and then thou ſhalte ſaye true.</p>
               <p>Let vs now diſcouer thy ſecond head, or chiefe poynte, importing the third repetitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the oath made at the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of Bloys. For anſwere hereunto I ſay, that I would haue thee to remember thy ſelfe for the third reiteration, that the firſt &amp; generalloath which the Noblemem haue made to their king and countrey, ought not to be violated by an incidentall cauſe of the vnfaithfulnes and treaſon of the Guize, when as he rebelled againſt his king. Nowe to the purpoſe of thy repetition. Thou doeſt ſtill repe at heere the zeale of the Pagans, the which thou doeſt alwayes commend and approoue, as if it were not knowne that the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8747:38"/>wiſeſt amongſt them would mocke at thy pretended ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime, ſeeing that they woulde chuſe that which Cicero ſpeaketh of in his book De Amicitia,
<note place="margin">Cice lib. de Amic.</note> to be more profitable and of more aſſurance, which ſaith, that all things that are profitable for the common-wealth, are the beſt diuinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that may bee found out and done: amongſt the which in the mean time conſiſted the chiefeſt part of the Pagans religion. Cato alſo came to that pointe, when as hee gaue councell to appeaſe God with the incenſe, and to let the calfe grow for the plough. To be ſhort, this was a ſubtletie wherwith the wiſeſt amongſt the Gentils did ſerue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their religions. And thou doeſt the like in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thy ſelfe to accuſe Noblemen with indeuouring to bring in hereſie into France, the which thou calleſt Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme. It it keth mee to repeate one thing ſo often, it hath beene already anſwered, that the Noblemen are bound to maintaine the eſtate of the kings of the countrey, and that in many thinges your Church hath neede of reformation. Theſe two propoſitions, in ſteade of maintaining hereſie, do incounter with it, &amp; beat it down. To the which ſpeech thou doſt adde, that the furie of heretikes, ioined with the ſoueraigne power, beeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſo bloudy, that it neuer lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the Catholicks at reſt, and doeſt take examples from ſome Infidels, being perſecuters of the Church, to witnes which they bring againſt the barbarouſnes of Caluin, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe than that of the Arrians. Thus thou ſaieſt. But in the mean time ſearch the holy ſcriptures, &amp; thou ſhalt find that this is done by the murderer of Rome,
<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> to maintayne his pride, his tyranny, &amp; his apoſtacie, by the horrible mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which hee hath committed throughout all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſince that his filthines hath been diſcouered. And as touching Caluin, his life, deeds, &amp; writings, do abhor ſuch deuiliſh cruelties (as amongſt other things) that which he faith vpon this text of the Romanes doth witneſſe, which ſaith;
<note place="margin">Rom 12.</note> Bleſſe them that perſecute you: whe upon he writeth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8747:38"/>thus, foraſmuch as it is moſt harde to obſerue and retayne ſuch a mildnes and ſweetnes, ſo much more we ought to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to attaine it. For our ſauiour would that we ſhould be different from the wicked, as alſo that no man canne name himſelfe the child of God, if he bee not clothed with ſuch a courage: and afterward he addeth, that we ought to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the ſaluation of thoſe which doe drawe damnation vppon themſelues. Beholde now the ſpeeches of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, declaring the wrong which thou doeſt to his renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medneſſe, and to his writings. And now to come vnto thy examples, I ſaie, that the aforeſayd teſtimonie doth a great deale better reſemble you to Achab, Iezabel, Valens, Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and others of the ſame race, than thoſe to whome thou doeſt compare it, as in deede thou canſt not obiect anie one maſſacre to be auouched by the reformed Church, but wee may iuſtly, truely, and entirely, obiect againſt you all thoſe that haue bene done in Chriſtendome anie time within this fiftie yeeres becauſe of religion: from whence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that this text of the Prophet hath beene accompliſhed amongſt you, the which thou doeſt alledge to this purpoſe againſt vs, <hi>Superbia corum qui te oderunt aſcendit se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per.</hi> The pride of thoſe which hate thee, doth alwaies manifeſt it ſelfe. Alſo beholde thy ſecond chiefe point diſcouered, and now let vs laie open thy thirde, wherewith thou doeſt ſo greatly charge thy aduerſaries with brutiſhnes, &amp; where thou ſaieſt that the Catholiks which defend theyr king and their Countrie, are more void of reaſon than beaſts, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt the cranes, eagles, &amp; the hony bee to witnes, which wil neuer admit anie to their king, but one of the ſame kinde. To this I ſaie, that the example of the Crane, beeing a verie dull and hurtfull bird, may bee verie well applyed vnto thy ſelfe. Firſt, becauſe thou doeſt exhorte the fooliſh amongſt the French men, to be like cranes, and ſo change their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which is now moſt free, into one that is moſt ſeruile and miſerable, imitating the aſſe, which deſireth to ſerue
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8747:39"/>the Tanner, rather than anie other maiſter.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Cranes doo eate vp the ſeede from the earth, and thou wouldeſt haue the French men to be eaten vp of the Spaniardes. The examples of the Eagles is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able vnto the ſame, for they are great gourmandiſers of the fleſh of beaſts and foules, which doe not liue vppon anie praie: in this thy drift is ſhewed to bee nothing elſe, but to haue the good people to be deuoured. Furthermore, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles flic verie farre, and ſo wouldeſt thou haue the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens libertie, and the Pirence mountaines flie into Spaine. Alaſſe, then what ſhould become of our citizens, parents, wiues, and children? From whence commeth this, that in ſtead of imitating Bees, which are profitable, thou doeſt imitate thoſe droue Bees, or rather dragons, which doe wound verie ſore. And if the queſtion bee in this, that thou wouldeſt applie the thing to the imitating of creatures, that is altogether agaynſt thee, becauſe the French men are more bound to follow the Prince of their owne nature and nation, than a Spaniard which is their enimie, &amp; of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie humor to theirs. But becauſe here thou wouldeſt walke more warily with thy treaſon, &amp; ſale of thy Countrie: thou doeſt heere agayne imploie the difference of religion. Whereunto I aunſwere, that murders and maſſacres are not the next waies to decide and auoyde the controuerſies, remember that which is aforeſayde, and let the promiſe be mutually diſcharged, without comming anie kinde of way to this madde extremitie, in putting vs into the handes of the Spaniardes, euen as thy councell doeth aduiſe, beeing drawen from the dungeons of hell.</p>
               <p>But beholde the miſchiefe, which ſtoppeth the paſſage to this ordinarie waie: for you, euen you doe mocke and ſcorne maliciouſlie, and againſt your conſcience, becauſe the king doeth offer himſelfe to come to that, in ſaying that it is but fayned and altogether contrarie, ſeeing that hee hath promiſed neuer to chaunge his religion; and thou
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8747:39"/>doeſt adde moreouer, that there needeth not anie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, ſeeing that wee neede neuer call the Catholike Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh religion into anie doubt.</p>
               <p>Finally, thou doeſt conclude, that there is no need to attende eppon anie councell, becauſe the king doeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but deceiue the Catholikes with ſuch vaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. But becauſe thou ſhouldeſt not go vnanſwered, wee ſaie, that laying aſide your lyes, excuſes, and craftie ſhiftes, which tend to no other purpoſe, but to turne back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes and flie from the liſtes, that the Chriſtian kinges ought to bee carefull for the wholeſome religion, and to procure conuocations of Synodes and Councels, when as they are duely aduertiſed, that there is anie abuſe, error, or ſuperſtition brought into the Church,
<note place="margin">Deut. 17. 1. Cor. 14.</note> ſeeing that God commaundeth them to keepe the whole wordes of his lawe, as beeing diſpoſers of the ſame. This duetie was inioyned to Dauid, to diſtribute and giue vnto the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of Aaron theyr right places and ordinaunces, which were before refuſed in their charges. By this ſame commaundement alſo,
<note place="margin">2. Kin. 22.</note> Ioſias commaunded Helkiah the high Prieſt to repayre the temple, and to praie vnto the Lorde, as well for the king as for the people, and to the ſame ende hee aſſembled the Prophettes and the high Prieſtes, with the aforeſayde people, to reade before them all the booke of the Lawe. Hee alſo cauſed the Paſſe-ouer to bee celebrated, and deſtroyed the idolatrie amongſt the Romane Emperours. Theodoſe the great aſſembled the Councell of Conſtantinople agaynſte the hereſie of the Macedonians. In many other places it is apparaunt, that diuerſe Councells haue bene aſſembled for ſuch like errour.</p>
               <p>But at this daie it is a queſtion, of greate corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beeing brought into the Church by the pride and couetouſneſſe of the Biſhoppes of Rome, in ſo much
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8747:40"/>as one onely may nowe refuſe a ſynodale conuocation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thoſe that can proue, that the infinite neſſe of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in the ſame, haue corrupted and falſefied the true ſeruice of God. Oh what tyrannie and mallice is this, but to feare leaſt that your turpitude and filthineſſe ſhould be further diſcouered, is the cauſe of the refuſall thereof: one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe but prepare your ſelues to enter into conference, if there bee anie neede, and then ſhall yee finde whether there ſhall bee anie faining on our partes or not. But yee care nothing at all to haue it, following the Italian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, which ſaith, <hi>Chiſta ben non ſi inuoua.</hi> He that is well, let him keepe him ſo. Yee liue at your eaſe in all delightes and idlenes, rather making thoſe beleeue which ſearch out your abuſes, <hi>Quod ſunt infideles &amp; dubii in fide.</hi> That they are vnfaithfull and weake of beleefe. As thou ſayeſt, whileſt that in the meane time you doublie cloake your ſelues with crafte and ſubtilties, for the which cauſe yee neither require Synode nor councell, ſo fearefull art thou that the king will goe to maſſe, ſaying, that hee ought not to bee truſted although hee woulde ſaie ſo. Thy Engliſh pretended Catholike companion fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red likewiſe the ſame, but thou haſt the aun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>were vnto it, looke therein what hath beene ſayd vnto him, and for the reſt, thou ſhalt finde in Saint Iohn, that life euerlaſting conſiſteth in the knowledge of the onely true God, and of him which hee hath ſent, Chriſt Ieſus, and the king moſt Chriſtian-like hath proteſted to continue in the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Thou haſt therefore theſe thirtie times ſhewed thy ſelfe to bee an impudent ſlanderer, when as thou doeſt compare him vnto prophane kinges which haue abuſed religion, in ſeeking vnder the coulour of the ſame, to inſtal and bring in their tyrannies. Now lette vs ſee wherefore thou doeſt accuſe the king of periurie. After that he had ſworne, ſayeſt thou, that hee woulde not innouate anie thing for the ſpace of ſixe moneths, incontinentlie hee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8747:40"/>made a ſtatute at Tours, by the which hee dooth diſpence with the regulars, as concerning their obedience which they owe vnto their ſuperiors, if they will aduertiſe him of thoſe things which they ſhould vndertake againſt him, &amp; dooth inioyne the confeſſors to declare the confeſſions of the Catholickes in the ſame behalfe. What Diuine or Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitian I praye you, is this? A king commaundeth his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes to declare vnto him thoſe which conſpire agaynſt his perſon, or againſt his eſtate of gouernement; Ergo hee is periured, if he inquireth of traitors who haue ſworne to do it. But in deſpite of the rage which cauſeth theſe furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to bee ſo madde: I demaunde, who is the chiefe in a kingdome, if the ſoueraigne Magiſtrate be not? Next vnto God, who ought a man to ſweare faith and fidelitie vnto, but onely vnto the ſoueraigne Magiſtrate? Are not the lawes in this caſe cleare and formable enough, that is to ſay, that the ſubiect is culpable of the crime or treaſon, if he doth not reueale vnto him the conſpiracies which are pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt him. But one hath promiſed and ſworn not to ſay any thing. I anſwere, that it hath beene proued, that it is not lawfull to ſweare to doe euill; and if it be that any hath ſo ſworne, that then he ought preſently to cal it back agayne and repent, leaſt that the ſecond ſinne bee woorſe than the firſt. Moreouer, true it is, that that which preſſeth thee without compariſon, is the feare of hanging of ſome Monke or Prieſt. Wherupon thou oughteſt to vnderſtand, that the crime of treaſon againſt his ſoueraigne, is worthy to be made hanging, aſwell towards the Eccleſiaſticall, as toward the Nobilitie, and aſwel towards the councellors, as the Merchants.</p>
               <p>Now let vs heare thy propheſie. If the king of Nauarre were head ouer the French Church, that of theſe two faire heades ſhould Antichriſt be borne: for hee would (ſayeſt thou) take away religion from the Frenchmen, &amp; bring in a moſt cruell French inquiſition. To the which alſo I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8747:41"/>that the Church neither ought nor can haue but one heade,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 1 1. Theſ. 2</note> which is Chriſt Ieſus. Secondly, that Antichriſt is borne long time ſince. Thirdly, that the king had rather die a hundred and a hundred times, than to take away the Chriſtian religion from France, not hauing any thing at all determined in his mind to bring in any inquiſition what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, ſo far off is it from being like to that of Spayne, the which thou calleſt iuſte, (but thou haſt omitted, amongſt the deuils in hell) ſeeing that his vnſpeakable crueltie and tyranny is not exerciſed but amongſt thoſe who are moſt religious, according to the will of God, and moſt iuſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men: the which is knowne of all noble hartes lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the truth, and vertue. And becauſe ye hate ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ye doe the more commend ſuch a kind of Inquiſition: foraſmuch as it hurteth none but them, for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of your ambition, auarice, ſuperſtition, cookry, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and tyranny. Beholde how the treatie of religion is in Spayne, the Soueraigne is altogether robbed and ſpoyled of the knowledge that a Magiſtrate ought to haue ouer his ſubiectes, when as there is any capitall crime commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or any other corporall puniſhments to be vſed, vppon what occaſion ſoeuer it be: for all men knowe, that king Philip, through a pretended deuotion, hath giuen &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported this right whereof we ſpeake, vnto his Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Romiſh Spanyardes, which haue deſired and wreſted it from him, by all the moſt ſubtill cooſenages, and deceits that any kinde of way they could deuiſe to bring the ſame to paſſe, that therby they might the more ſubtilly vſe their deueliſh &amp; cruel actions, agaynſt thoſe which do but once open their eyes againſt theyr errors, trumperies, and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods.</p>
               <p>And all this husbandrying intituleth it ſelfe, the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spayne, the which giueth ſuch authoritie &amp; bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto his Clergie, that they dare quarrell with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the bloud, and challenge them, euen ſo farre foorth,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8747:41"/>as to the razing of them out, ſo as is already come to paſſe. Where is to be vnderſtood, that the Soueraigne prince did neuer rule more imperiouſly ouer Spaine, than theſe ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Lord gouernors doe by the miniſterie of this Inquiſition, which maketh them to liue like kinges, and princes, and in aſſurance, being moſt aſſured, that theyr filthines and deceits ſhall neuer fall into any examination or cenſure, but amongſt themſelues. Now this is the cauſe that this Leaguerer and his companions, finding all this to be ſo good, according to their mind, why they would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly eat a part of it. And for the attaining vnto the which (ſayeſt thou) that it is better to take a king of a ſtraunge nation, that is to ſay, a Spanyard, daring to aſſure thy ſelfe that by the office and ſeruice of his Inquiſition, this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſis would worke well for thee and thy mates, ſo that of ſimple prieſtes and prelates, ye might become little kings, like vnto your vſurping Spanyards.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt a natutall pretended reaſon indeede, and goe on with it, ſeeing that Satan hath no more expedient meanes to maintayne your ambition, couetouſnes, tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and idlenes by.</p>
               <p>But for feare of beeing accuſed of accuſing a king of Spayne with ſuch like ignorance and vndiſcreetnes, being reputed wiſe amongſt all the monarchies of the earth, it behoueth me to eſchue ſuch a blame, in diſcouering his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and to what ende he propoſeth himſelfe, when as hee giueth the iuriſdiction and power, which euery Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ought to keepe himſelfe, when hee ſhould miniſter the criminall puniſhment which belongeth vnto his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, vpon what occaſion ſoeuer, to his eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. For there is no cauſe why we ſhould eſteem or think, that one onely and ſuperſtitious indiſcretion doth induce this great prince to ſuch wicked proceedinges: wee ſhall finde and conclude then, that in making this preſent Inquiſition actiuelye vnto hys Cleargie, hee hath
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8747:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:8747:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:8747:43"/>imitated the ſubtill proceedinges of Mahomet, the which beeing not able to inſtall his tyranny amongſt the Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, imployed himſelfe vnder the colour of religion, by the miniſterie of the which hee executed his wickedneſſe more eaſily. But had not ſuch a ſubtletie beene, the eſtates of Spayne had hindred their king well enough from biting and kicking ſo furiouſly as he doth now, and as the codi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and leſſon of thoſe of Arragon do witneſſe, beginning thus. We which can doe more than yee, wee chuſe you for king, with ſuch conditions &amp;c. By the meanes whereof, they had expulſed from them this tyranny, had it not been for the ſubtleties and villainous aide of their wretched ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall prieſtes? What preachers are theſe, which by their exhortations, preachings, and authorities, doe helpe to maintaine this deuiliſh inquiſition, with the which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice theſe venerable perſonages doe acquite themſelues the more willingly, becauſe that in ſteade of feeling theyr part of the tyranny, they make it ſerue to their greatneſſe, immunities, honours, pleaſures, commodities, and other ſuch like benefites comming and iſſuing from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid inquiſition. Behold alſo now the motiue and efficient cauſe of the ſame, where it appeareth, that aſwel the king, as the Clergie of Spayne, do complot, ſucke, and gripe the people, ouer whom God hath conſtituted them, as fathers and guides. What religious people be theſe which ſporte themſelues thus with poore Chriſtians, ſending them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caiphas to Pilate? For which cauſe, two euident exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples will witneſſe, that the zeale of religion hath nothing at all induced neither the king of Spayne to ſhew himſelfe chiefe of the Leaguerers, nor the Leaguerers which are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ſeditious Frenchmen, to rebell agaynſt theyr king.</p>
               <p>The firſt example heereof is taken from the ſodayne death of the two laſt Popes, beeing diſpatched by a letter of exchange, hauing adioyned vnto it the Schiſme which
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8747:43"/>the ſame Spaniard had brought into the towne of Rome, where I demand, that if the king of Spaine be ſo affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto his religion, wherefore doth hee not reſpect him whome hee holdeth and acknowledgeth as the lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, and to be a ſpirituall Father? One may ſee then, that by ſuch workmanſhips he would haue vs to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that whoſoeuer ſhall not bee in the nature of a Spaniard, ſhal neuer be accounted a good Romiſh Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Laſtly, the other example commeth from the towne of Soiſſons, the Leaguers of the which, by the ordinaunce of their ſuperiours (as they call them) haue chaſed out the ladie Abbeſſe from the aforeſoid Soiſſons, being the kings Aunt (where ſhe hath alwaies beene preſerued both from the one and the other) notwithſtanding that they knowe, that ſhe is the moſt ancient princeſſe of the bloud, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted of all, for the moſt zealous &amp; affectionate vnto the Catholike Romane religion which is in the world. An e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident token, that a ſpirit which is the author of confuſion and ſedition, doth vrge the furies of ſuch Leaguers, &amp; not the zeale of religion. Poore Catholiks &amp; vnaduiſed, which do affect ſo much that tyrannicall Spaniſh gouernment, conſider here the intention and purpoſe of your eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall leaguers, which do ſo much priſe and praiſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of ſuch a climate, yea, euen as of brideled calues, if there bee anie perſeuerance in ſuch blindneſſe. Aſſure your ſelues, moſt miſerable French men, that the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the moſt valiant, the moſt vertuous, the moſt aduiſed, the moſt wiſe, the moſt learned, the moſt iuſt, and the moſt rich amongſt you, ſhall euermore vnder ſuch a ſchoolma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, be accounted and holden as heretikes, if it commeth to paſſe, that ye bee not found in all things agreeable vnto maiſter Inquiſitor. Then ye ſhall vnderſtand by them, that the maſſe ſhall not ſaue you. To this purpoſe, two exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (among a thouſand, which came vnto my knowledge a few daies ſithence) ſhall open this text. It came to paſſe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8747:44"/>that two marchants of Gaſcoigne being in Spain, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the high waie, did contemplate and beholde an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, being much poliſhed and verie faire, and ſhining as bright as anie of their Countrie, whereuppon they tooke occaſion betweene themſelues, to demaund whether that matter whereof it was made, was either of ſtone or wood. This was inough to be ſayd in Spaine, they were heard by one of the Inquiſitors, and preſently lead vnto a miſerable priſon, wherein they remained the ſpace of three whole yeres after, notwithſtanding any proteſtations or prooues they could make or bring for the triall of theyr being Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks. And the other example is this. A man of Poictou, a great Catholike, being at Lisborne, ſeeing a great Prieſt, beeing graue, fayre, and in good habite, and marching ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: this man began to ſaie (thinking to haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Prieſt,) Beholde a Prieſt (ſaith hee) and not one of the durtie Prieſts of Poictou. This being but once ſpoken, which was inough, immediatly this Poicteuni is heard &amp; vnderſtood, and therevpon lead preſently <hi>in dome Petri,</hi> into the popes priſon, where he was kept ſafe for the ſpace of ſixe moneths, without knowing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, about the end of which tearme, he was commaunded that he ſhould not cal Prieſts Durtie any more. There may be a whole booke compoſed of theſe tyrannies and vniuſt dealings. Theſe effects of the Inquiſition will be found &amp; proued true, and not thy conceit of anie Catholikes to bee puniſhed by the magiſtrates of that religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land or in Bearne, as hath beene els where ſaid. Thoſe to whome it appertayneth, knowe that ſuch offenders were puniſhed in the quality of the ſeditious, &amp; not as being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious. From thence thou turneſt for this ſeuententh time, to leape vpon the authoritie of the Popes: ſaying, that the king is not the ſon of the church, becauſe he wold not kiſſe his pantable. To the which I ſay againe, that it hath beene proued vnto thee, that it is enough for him, that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8747:44"/>church is his mother, &amp; that the Romiſh church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him this liberty &amp; priuilege. And for that thou doeſtalwaies feare ſome eccleſiaſticall reformation, neuer deſiring any other religion, than that which feedeth the belly, thou threateneſt the noblemen with their going to hell, if they do not helpe to maintaine thy cauſe. Hereupon harken I pray ye to the preacher: I ſhould loue it better ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou, that ye were Huguenits, &amp; ſo to ſee you fight for vs Catholiks. Marke I pray ye, he holdeth that the Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nits are damned: whereupon it followeth, that hee ſhould haue nothing to do with condemning of thoſe Catholikes of whome he ſpeaketh, ſeeing that they ſhould defend the kitchin his mother. Behold alſo how he calleth the Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nits to the ſame defence. Thou art in thy triumph: but goe to with thy Lyntill broth, to the which thou doeſt allude. To be ſhort, thou art greeued diuerſly, becauſe the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which are the principall force of the realme, will not vnderſtand all this. Thou haſt bin told, that they are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently bound, aſwel to defend their king, as their cuntry, together with their honors, liberties, &amp; piuiledges: yea &amp; the more, becauſe they are bearded with the Spanyard, an ancient enemy, vnto whom ye would willingly ſell htem. Therefore remember thy ſelfe of the anſwer that was giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the robbers which pleaded againſt the merchantes, for carrying weapons to defend themſelues. Thou doeſt heere repeat for the 70. time the difference hapned in France for religion. The which here againe I ſay, haue been moued by your clergie, &amp; els where hath beene anſwered in ſo many ſortes, and ſo often, that it is more than enough. And now turne again thy leafe. Thou doſt heap vp afterwards, proud maieſticall words of thine owne deuiſing, thinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the better to gette the Noblemen on thy ſide: but thou oughteſt to ſerue thy ſelfe with concluding reaſons, and not with affecting wordes, throwne into the aire, to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning of all that which might happen to come after.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:8747:45"/>
               <p>And how doeſt thou torment thy ſelfe in vaine on this ſide? alſo it is to no purpoſe, that thou doeſt propoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aforeſaide noble men, the examples of the moſt excellent Romane knights, as that of Sceuola, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thou malitious blind, doeſt thou not ſee, that it was for the ſame cauſe of defence, that Sceuola burnt his hand, and that the others imploied themſelues in the defence of their Countrie. It is true, that thou makeſt great account of the Iacobin that kild the laſt king, the which thou doeſt produce againe, as in a triumph, vſing theſe great wordes. One that was religious hath flaine the king of France, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing giuen teſtimonie of his zeale vnto all France. O mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable bloudie man, thou haſt had here before alledged vnto thee, the ſentence which the ſpirit of God pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt ſuch qualified murderers, ſaying that the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of iniquitie are in their tabernacles,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. 19.</note> &amp; curſed be their furie, for it is impudencie. The nobles and valiant Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes which thou doeſt exhort vnto the ſame curſed furie, will anſwere thee, that they wil not giue entertaiment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the deuill being a murderer, as thy Iacobin companion did, when he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew the king: &amp; no otherwiſe, but as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Iudas when hee betraied his maſter Chriſt vnto the Iewes.
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> And as thou wouldeſt ſerue thy ſelfe with ſuch examples, for the execution of ſuch a qualified wickednes, ſo likewiſe wouldeſt thou, that the name of a Catholike might ſerue for another hang-man, when as thou ſayeſt, if the name of a Catholike bee common vnto vs, why not weapons alſo. But to better purpoſe will the nobles aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thee, and ſaie, that if the name of Chriſtians doeth admoniſh all French men to one mutuall duetie, why then doe not yee rather ioyne with vs then with the Spaniard? And vppon thy repeated obiection; where againe thou doeſt accuſe them to bee mercenaries, they will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere thee, that they defend theyr king becauſe of theyr duetyes aboue mentioued, and not otherwiſe. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8747:45"/>to thee and thy companions, to defende that parte which may maintaine your pottage potte. Thou replieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and ſaieſt; But if this be an article of your faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the Catholicke church, and leaue out the Romane, what ſhall become of your faith? They will anſwere thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for the tenth time, that it is enough for them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the Catholike chriſtian church, which hath for obiect Chriſt Ieſus, and his promiſes, &amp; not the traditions,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5</note> nor the Biſhoppe of Rome. The faithfull, that bee vnited vnto this church, neede not go to viſite the monuments of Paleſtina, wherof thou here ſpeakeſt, ſeeing that they are the children of the Ieruſalem from on high,
<note place="margin">Eph. 2. Rom 4. Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Mat. 6. Ephe. 1. Rom. 4.</note> which doth deliuer and ſette them free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch, &amp; other ſuch like ſeruitude. This church, is the mother of our king, approued of the eſtates, and iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the iuſtice of Fraunce, to bee in the princes qualitie, hauing right to raigne and commaund there notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; in deſpite of thy contradictions. In ſumme, and for concluſion of this article, we ſay, that we obtaine life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting in the chriſtian church, by the faith which is builded vpon the only word of God, the which doth teach,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> propoſe &amp; preſent, aſwel vnto the noblemen, as vnto others, the way and means how to be inriched, and honored with life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, in the heauens, which truſt &amp; hope in God, and in his promiſes, by the onely meane and benefite of the death, paſſion, reſurrection,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> and aſcention of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt which dyed for our ſins, and roſe againe for our iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and which hath been giuen to vs by God for wiſdome, iuſtice, ſanctification, and redemption: and finally, which aſcended into heauen, there to prepare a place for vs, and to receiue vs th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, to the ende that we may liue with him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, in a perfect eſtate offelicitie and bleſſednes. Theſe beleefs and promiſes doe ſuffice the faithfull, without that, that there is any need to adioine the inuentions and traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Pope of Rome, which are hurtful, in ſtead of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting vnto ſaluation. All thoſe which do liue in this attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8747:46"/>and hope, (aboue all humane duerie) will haue in ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne commendation, the honor &amp; obedience which they owe vnto their ſoueraigne Magiſtrates, and the duties that they are bound to yeeld vnto their countrey. By this meanes the almightie beeing moſt liberall and mercifull, ſhall giue them the peace of conſcience, in cauſing their labour to bee profitable, to his glorie, and the good of the Realme, and of the King, to the generall contentment of all thoſe, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to liue according to the will of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The generall Concluſion.</head>
               <p>ALL which ſaid Articles, being approued and verefied, do declare the author of the aforeſaide falſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; ſuppoſitions, not onely to be an impudent ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, but guiltie in all, &amp; by all the enormeous crimes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee hath falſly accuſed his ſoueraigne prince, together with thoſe which acknowledg him as their king. S. Iude ſaith that Michael the Archangell durſt not giue any curſed ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt the deuil, but ſaith, the Lord rebuke thee, whiles that thou wicked creature, like to a brute beaſt, doeſt miſcall Lordſhippes, the inſtitution and dignitie of the which, thou wouldſt malitiouſly ſtand in doubt of, following the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the children of Chore. It would be better for thee to remember, that the wrath of the king, is as the meſſenger of death:
<note place="margin">Prou. 16.</note> but the wiſe man will pacifie it. Thou canſt not deny, but that thy infamous writings wretchedly written, brought to a lawfull Monarch, ſuch a one as he of France, doe declare thee to be the head and chiefe of prophane lyers, and decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers: and ſo much the more excellent in the art of falſly ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, and euill ſpeaking of Lordſhips and honors, by how much the more (like to the example of Satan) thou beeing diſguiſed into an Angell of light, doeſt ſerue thy ſelfe ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; malitiouſly, with ſome true maximes (as they are in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) the which thou doeſt diuert and wreſt from their true
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8747:46"/>ſence, and right application, to the intrapping by treaſon, deſolation, and ruine of Fraunce. And thus will I ſhutte vp this preſent diſcourſe by this briefe concluſion, as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the abuſe brought in by the Biſhops of Rome, which ſheweth your religion (being Romiſh) to be infamous, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the moſt religious and learned in Europe.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1. Ye make of your high and moſt worthy eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call charge, a ſtorehouſe of ambition, auarice, idolatrie, and ſuperſtition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Ye haue in ſtead of Chriſt Ieſus and his Vicars, placed the moſt corrupt men in all Chriſtendome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Ye haue adnihilated the commaundementes of God, and haue authorized the traditions which were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Cittie of Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 Ye cauſe the ſgnes of the ſacraments to be woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as God, and afterwards falling into another er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ye baptize your bels, and your ſhips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 To witnes your tyranny and falſhood, ye will not ſuffer your doctrine to be examined by the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 In ſtead of obeying your ſoueraigne Magiſtrate, ye ſhew your ſelues rebels, and not ſo content, but alſo yee ſeeke to maſſacre him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 Your corruption is ſo farre beyond meaſure, that to ſpeake of regeneration, and the truth amongst you, is accounted hereſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 Ye ſing your Maſſes likewiſe for the helth of beaſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 Ye do apply to the condition of thoſe, the cenſure of excommunication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 Ye ſhew the ſhamefulparts of your Biſhop to prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at the inſtalling of his pontificall office, and yee make them to kiſſe his feet, in ſuch ſort as was done to Caligula.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:8747:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>All which patches, and infinite others, beeing brought together, do ſhew and vereſie, that there hath neuer beene any Pagan nation, or people that haue ſo much ſported with, or mocked God, &amp; his religion, as yee doo: and then in wiping the mouth,
<note place="margin">Prou. 30.</note> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the whore doth, of whom Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon ſpeaketh, ye ſay, I haue done no iniquitie. And not contente with that, yee impute it vnto the iuſt, who neuer thought it. I haue no more to ſay to thee heere at this time, but that the paſſions of the ſoule do alwaies produce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effects to their ends and deſires.
<note place="margin">Plut. in mor.</note>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 28. for naturall, reade materiall Page 1. line 4. for repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, read approoued. Page 11. line 1. for the which idolatrie, reade to the which idolatrie. Page 12. line 4. for approueth, read and approueth. &amp; line 26. for the pretended, reade thy pretended. Page 14. line 29. for there, vead theſe. Page 16. line 26. for far off is it, read ſo far off is it. Page 17. line 6. for nor, read not. Pag. 19. line 7. for by word, read by the word Page 25. line 9. for then hath, read then hee hath. Page 30. line 27 for Proctor, read Doctor. &amp; line 30. for Lutheran, read Latheran. Page 32. line 2. for if in deede, read it is indeede Page 33. line 31. for chan, reade than. Page 35. line 23. for in a part, read a part. Page 36. line 11. for be erroneous, read to be erroneous. Page 37. line 28. for inſeperation, read inſpiration. Page 43. line 28. for in affaires, reade in the affaires Page 46. line 1 for of, read if. &amp; line 18. for our, read out. &amp; line 30. for of mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, read of the maiadies. Page 48. for Bartolwes, read Bartholmewes. &amp; line 26. for thou, read that thou. Page 49. line 11. for my, read any Pa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. line 29. for Criminate, read Criminall. Page 52 line 29. for Maxiome. read Axiome.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8747:47"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
